<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scarronnides, or, Virgile travestie a mock-poem, in imitation of the fourth book of Virgils Æneis in English, burlesque.</title>
            <author>Cotton, Charles, 1630-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2518</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12697696</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12697696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34645)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 684:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scarronnides, or, Virgile travestie a mock-poem, in imitation of the fourth book of Virgils Æneis in English, burlesque.</title>
                  <author>Cotton, Charles, 1630-1687.</author>
                  <author>Virgil. Aeneis Liber 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 156, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Cotes for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Charles Cotton. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Virgil. --  Aeneis --  Liber 4 --  Parodies, imitations, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65925:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65925:1"/>
            <p>Scarronnides: <hi>OR,</hi> VIRGILE Traveſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Mock-Poem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In imitation of the Fourth Book of <hi>Virgils Aeneis</hi> in <hi>Engliſh, Burleſque.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Stultiſſimum credo ad imitandum non optima quaeque pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re. <bibl>Plin. Epiſt. 5. lib. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Roger L'eſtrange.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Cotes</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane.</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:65925:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65925:2"/>
            <head>UPON <hi>VIRGILE Traveſtie,</hi> the Fourth BOOK.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>W. B.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </byline>
            <lg>
               <l>TEll us how he by her command<note place="margin">Inſandum Regina, jubes. lib. 2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Told ſtories which ſhould be <hi>infand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which neither <hi>Faith nor Troth</hi> would hold,</l>
               <l>If not by <hi>Jones</hi> or him been told;</l>
               <l>Yet this muſt needs obtain more credit</l>
               <l>And be believ'd by thoſe that read it;</l>
               <l>Whileſt <hi>Jones by th' arm of fleſh</hi> did doot,</l>
               <l>This man had all the <hi>Gods to boot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which ſince hath taught ſome folks to ſay as</l>
               <l>He us'd to ſay, <hi>Sum pius Anaeas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Self-commendations ſeem but odly,</l>
               <l>When themſelves call themſelves <hi>the Godly:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For my part they may <hi>ſave their labours,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis a ſign they <hi>live by ill Neighbours:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:65925:3"/>
               <l>By others hands they may be painted</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Devils,</hi> who by their own are <hi>Sainted.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But oh, <hi>In's ſleep, Mercury</hi> chid him</l>
               <l>From that looſe company, and bid him</l>
               <l>Haſte for a <hi>Kingdom</hi> for <hi>Iülus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe children might hereafter rule us,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Revelating Spirits</hi> thus we ſee</l>
               <l>Obtained was the<note n="a" place="margin">For <hi>Aeneas</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome 100 of years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dido</hi> built <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fourth Monarchy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Harriſon</hi> and <hi>Vane</hi> ventured a lift</l>
               <l>By the ſame Spirit for a <hi>Fift.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor had <hi>Anaeas</hi> fared better,</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Dido</hi> ever ſeen the Traytour<note n="b" place="margin">The <hi>Roman.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chaſt Queen</hi> to be abus'd by ſtory,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virgil</hi>'s infamy, as <hi>Virgil</hi>'s glory.</l>
               <l>But let's proceed (though all muſt know it</l>
               <l>A ſtory falſe) along with <hi>Poet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Look into the <hi>Cave</hi> at all his bravity,</l>
               <l>And ſhewing <hi>tricks</hi> of hid <hi>concavity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For what did he there, pray! with <hi>Dido,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No more then either you or Ide do:</l>
               <l>What! His thick Runn—ſtretched <hi>Dido,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her <hi>omicron</hi> into a wide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>Then let's not make't nor worſe nor better,</l>
               <l>He only <hi>circumflext</hi> a letter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus having got his will, he muſt</l>
               <l>Into the <hi>Sea</hi> make's ſecond thruſt:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:65925:3"/>
               <l>Nor can her threatnings nor beſeeches,</l>
               <l>Make him once more let down his br—</l>
               <l>But he'l away, ſo the advice is,</l>
               <l>Firſt by <hi>Mercury,</hi> then by <hi>Anchiſes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay to move ſtill i'th' <hi>godly faſhion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>zealot</hi> pleades<note n="c" place="margin">Fata obſtant; ſequimur te Sancte Deorum, Quiſquis es.</note> 
                  <hi>Pradeſtination.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let <hi>Nan, Right Reaſon</hi> urgent be,</l>
               <l>Yet with our <hi>Quakers, Hees not free;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fleſhy Religion plain treachery,</l>
               <l>To make the <hi>Gods</hi> pimp to their lechery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to go on, what's next lets ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hanging</hi> or <hi>wedding</hi>'s <hi>deſtinie;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou tells us how th' <hi>forſaken elſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſave her cloths did hang her ſelf:</l>
               <l>Where if ſome ſmall ſhe then bepiſt her,</l>
               <l>Yet they were made ſweet for her ſiſter</l>
               <l>With little Soap; for th' <hi>yellow water,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of which folks talk, makes ſo much matter,</l>
               <l>As if great ſtore run down her legg,</l>
               <l>Was not ſo much would <hi>ſweet an Egg.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Euphues</hi> the rope did prove,</l>
               <l>Defil'd his breeches for clean love:</l>
               <l>For if pure love (as people write)</l>
               <l>At firſt begins with <hi>ſhittle come ſh—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hers ending ſo was purely right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:65925:4"/>
               <l>But oh! How did her Siſter fare,</l>
               <l>Finding her dead as <hi>Moſs did's Mare:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVringing her hands, crying <hi>Eleza</hi>
               </l>
               <l>One would have thought ſhould been as wiſe a</l>
               <l>Nother? what haſt thou done oh <hi>Dido!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rather be hang'd then bear a <hi>by-blow:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then thumpt her breaſt and tore her hair,</l>
               <l>Cry'd <hi>Dido, Dido</hi> in her ear,</l>
               <l>Speak I beſeech thee, prethee ſpeak,</l>
               <l>Not one poor word for <hi>Siſters ſake!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But ſhe'd laid ſpeech, her time was come,</l>
               <l>And thus did <hi>Di-Do-end in Dum-Dum:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And left her Siſter a great fortune,</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>John Presbyter</hi> to importune.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65925:4"/>
            <head>VIRGILE TRAVESTIE.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Fourth Book.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>AT Regina gravi jamdudum ſaucia cura,</l>
                        <l>Vulnus alit venis, &amp; caeco carpitur igni.</l>
                        <l>Multa viri virtus animo, multuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> recurſat</l>
                        <l>Gentis honos, haerent infixi pectore vultus.</l>
                        <l>Verba<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> nec placidam membris dat cura quietens.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> IN this Fourth Book we find it written,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Dido</hi> Queen was deeply ſmitten;</l>
               <l>Much taken with the <hi>Trojan</hi>'s perſon,</l>
               <l>Than which a properer was ſcarce one:</l>
               <l>Much of his breeding did ſhe reckon,</l>
               <l>But more of what I'am loath to ſpeak on,</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65925:5"/>
               <l>For which ſhe did ſo ſcald and burn</l>
               <l>That none but he could ſerve her turn.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Poſtea <hi>Phoebea</hi> luſtrabat lampade terras,</l>
                        <l>Humentem<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Aurora polo dimovcrat umbram;</l>
                        <l>Cum ſic unanimem all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>quitur male ſana ſororem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> The Sun, that ſpruce light-headed fellow</l>
               <l>With frizled locks of ſanded yellow,</l>
               <l>The windows crept by radiation,</l>
               <l>Like ſon begot in fornication,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Dido</hi> mad for want of Man,</l>
               <l>Ev'n thus beſpake her Siſter <hi>Nan.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Annaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or, quae me ſuſpenſam inſomnia terrent?</note> I've been all night (quoth ſhe) my <hi>Nancy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So ſtrangely troubled in my fancy,</l>
               <l>I could not reſt till morning peep,</l>
               <l>Odd Dreams have ſo diſturb'd my ſleep.</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65925:5"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quis novus hic noſtris ſucceſſit ſedibus hoſpes?</l>
                        <l>Quem ſeſe ore ferens! quam forti pectore &amp; armis!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> What a ſtout ſtripling's this <hi>Aeneas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That thus has croſt the Seas to ſee us!</l>
               <l>I do believe, nay dare ſwear for him,</l>
               <l>No mortal woman ever bore him:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Credo equidem (nec vana fides) genus eſſe Deorum.</l>
                        <l>Degeneres animos timer arguit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But ſome great Lady in the skie,</l>
               <l>That nurſt him up with Furmitie!</l>
               <l>I hate a baſe cowardly drone,</l>
               <l>Worſe then a Rigil ten to One:</l>
               <l>But this bold <hi>Trojan</hi> I delight in;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Heu! quibus il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e</l>
                        <l>Jactatus fatis! Quae bella exhauſta canebat!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> How bravely does he talke of Fighting!</l>
               <l>I tell thee <hi>Nancy,</hi> wer't not that</l>
               <l>Folks would be apt to talk and prate,</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65925:6"/>
               <l>Should I ſo ſoon, new Suitors have,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ne cui me viaclo poſſum ſociare jugali,</l>
                        <l>Poſtquam Primus amor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Si non pertaeſum thalami tedae<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> fuiſſet,</l>
                        <l>Huic uni for ſan potui ſuccumbere culpae.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> My Husband yet ſcarce cold in's grave;</l>
               <l>And were I not with my firſt honey</l>
               <l>Half tyr'd as't' were with Matrimony,</l>
               <l>I could with this ſame youngſter tall,</l>
               <l>Find in my heart to try a fall.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Anna (fatebor enim) miſeri poſt fata Sychaei</l>
                        <l>Conjugis, &amp; ſparſos fraterna caede penates,</l>
                        <l>Solus hic inflexit ſenſus, animum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> labantem</l>
                        <l>Impulit: agnoſco veteris veſtigia flammae.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I muſt confeſs ſince that ſad ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pigmalion</hi> cut my Husbands weazen;</l>
               <l>This only (not to mince the matter)</l>
               <l>Is he has made my mouth to water.</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65925:6"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sed mibi vel tellus optem prius ima dehiſcat,</l>
                        <l>Aut pater omni potens adig at me——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But may I firſt <hi>Jove</hi> implore,</l>
               <l>Sinck thorow this my Chamber floor,</l>
               <l>Down quick into the Cellar's bottom,</l>
               <l>'Ere I commit the thing you wot on;</l>
               <l>Or any thing by luſt's ſuggeſtion,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Anti pudor quam te violem aut tua jura reſolvam.</note> That my good name may bring in queſtion.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Sic effata, ſinum lachrymis implevit obortis.</note> Which ſaid, ſhe wept in manner ampler,</l>
               <l>Than Girle new whipt for looſing Sampler.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nan</hi> in her Anſwer was not long,</l>
               <l>For nimble baggage of her tongue</l>
               <l>She was, (as ſome would ſay that knew her,</l>
               <l>As was in that or next Town to her.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65925:7"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Anna refert———</l>
                        <l>——O luce magis dilecta ſorori,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> O Siſter to me dearer farre</l>
               <l>Than Sunſhine dayes in harveſt are:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Solanè perpetuâ m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>rens carpere juventa?</l>
                        <l>Nec dulces natos Veneris nec praemia noris?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Wilt thou (quoth ſhe) O woman wood,</l>
               <l>Still ſtop the current of thy blood,</l>
               <l>And looſe the time by vain pretences</l>
               <l>Of making pretty Boyes and Wenches?</l>
               <l>Wilt thou cut faces evermore</l>
               <l>For Husband dead, as naile in door?</l>
               <l>Doſt thou believe, thou puling thing,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Id cinerem aut manes credis curare ſepultos?</note> That dead folks care for whimpering?</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65925:7"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Eſto; aegram nulli quondam flexere mariti;</note> Yield and be naught at laſt; y'ave plaid</l>
               <l>The fool too long, here be it ſaid,</l>
               <l>And ſtood too much in your own light,</l>
               <l>Or long enough ago, you might</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non Libyae; non ante Tyro deſpectus <hi>Iarbas,</hi> Ductoreſque alii quos <hi>Africa</hi> terr a triumphis</l>
                        <l>Dives alit, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Have match't your ſelf, and that well too,</l>
               <l>Torich and proper men enow.</l>
               <l>What though you have ſaid many nay,</l>
               <l>Yea, and burnt day-light, as we ſay,</l>
               <l>Goodman <hi>Iarbas</hi> here hard by,</l>
               <l>And others of good Yeomanry</l>
               <l>That might have paſt; becauſe forſooth</l>
               <l>They could not pleaſe your dainty tooth.</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:65925:8"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Placitone etiam pugnabis a mori?</l>
                        <l>Non venit in mentem, quorum conſeder is arvis?</l>
                        <l>Hinc Getulae urbes, genus inſuperabile bello,</l>
                        <l>Et Numidae infraeni cingunt, &amp; inhoſpita Syrtis</l>
                        <l>Hinc————</l>
                        <l>Barcaei.————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Muſt you ſtill mince it at this rate</l>
               <l>With that you would ſo fain be at?</l>
               <l>You nere conſider what a throng</l>
               <l>Of ſaucy Knaves you live among.</l>
               <l>Baſe ill-bred cheating ſurly currs,</l>
               <l>Raſcals as falſe, as Moor-Landers.</l>
               <l>Such fellows as I greatly doubt me,</l>
               <l>If you no better look about ye,</l>
               <l>And leave this fooliſh twittle twattle,</l>
               <l>To match with one may tent your cattle,</l>
               <l>Will in a ſhort ſpace not leave a Gooſe,</l>
               <l>Turky, or Hen about the houſe:</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:65925:8"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Germani<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> minas?——</note> Your Brother too, he ſwears and curſes</l>
               <l>About his Money baggs and purſes.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Diis equidem auſpicibus reor, &amp; Junone ſecunda</l>
                        <l>Huc curſum Iliacas vento tenuiſſe carinas.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I do believe that <hi>Jove</hi> and <hi>Juno,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Whom all the world, and I, and you know</l>
               <l>Have ever been your faithful friends)</l>
               <l>For ſome moſt ſecret courteous ends.</l>
               <l>Overblew <hi>Neptunes</hi> bouncing Ferries,</l>
               <l>Have hither ſent theſe <hi>Trojan</hi> Wherries.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh were theſe <hi>Trojans</hi> marry'd to us,</l>
               <l>What good ſuch bonny Lads might do us!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quam tu urbem ſoror hanc cernes! quae ſurgere regna</l>
                        <l>Coajugio tali! Teucrum comitantibus arm's</l>
                        <l>Punicaſe tantis attollet Gloria rebus!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> What a fine Town would ours be then</l>
               <l>How bravely ſtor'd with luſty Men!</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:65925:9"/>
               <l>Then without any more ado,</l>
               <l>Siſter ſay Grace, and ſo fall to:</l>
               <l>They in good manners ten to one,</l>
               <l>Will make an offer to be gone;</l>
               <l>And rather truſt their rotten Barges,</l>
               <l>Than ſtay to put you to more charges:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tu modo————</l>
                        <l>Indulge hoſpitio cauſaſque innecte morandi,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But you may make 'um at command,</l>
               <l>As eaſily ſtay as kiſs your hand.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Dum pelago deſaevit hyems, &amp; aquoſus Orion,</l>
                        <l>Quaſſ at aeque rates, nondum tractabile caelum.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Can you not tell 'um that the weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               </l>
               <l>'S too cold, or hot (no matter whether)</l>
               <l>Their Scullers torn, and ſhatter'd ſo,</l>
               <l>That they muſt mend 'um ere they go;</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:65925:9"/>
               <l>And in concluſion with good reaſon</l>
               <l>Wiſh 'um t' expect a better ſeaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>His dictis incenſum animum inflammavit amore,</l>
                        <l>Spemque dedit dubiae——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> With ſuch like documents as theſe are,</l>
               <l>Which the young-ſlut knew beſt would pleaſe her,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nancy</hi> ſo tickled up her Grace,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Dido</hi> ſcarce knew where ſhe was.</l>
               <l>Nay ſome affirm a dangerous matter,</l>
               <l>She'd much ado to hold her water:</l>
               <l>And counſail'd in that tempting ſtrain,</l>
               <l>I wonder how ſhe could contain:</l>
               <l>But certain 'tis, that this advice</l>
               <l>So wrought upon this Widow nice,</l>
               <l>That ſhe who Maid, Widow, and Wife,</l>
               <l>Had priz'd her honour, 'bove her life;</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65925:10"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">——<hi>Menti ſolvit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pudorem.</hi>
                  </note> Now car'd no more, for her good Name</l>
               <l>Than any common trading dame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Principio Delubra adeunt, pacemque per aras</l>
                        <l>Exquir a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t.———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But to the Church (forſooth) anon,</l>
               <l>That matters might go better on,</l>
               <l>Like people oth' Phanatick fry</l>
               <l>Who's ſanctities hypocriſie</l>
               <l>They muſt, and ſlipping on their Pattens</l>
               <l>They went, as who ſhould ſay to Mattens.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thither now come, fair <hi>Dido</hi> ſquats</l>
               <l>Her bum on baſſock made of Mats:</l>
               <l>For you muſt know, as ſtory ſayes,</l>
               <l>Queens, like the godly in theſe dayes,</l>
               <l>In manner inſolent and ſlightly,</l>
               <l>Diſdain'd to kneel to God Almighty.</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65925:10"/>
               <l>But <hi>Anna</hi> who was but a Spinſter,</l>
               <l>kneel'd low on ſtones as hard as flints are.</l>
               <l>Their eyes they rowl'd and bow'd their bodies</l>
               <l>To this, and t' other God and Goddeſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Legiferae <hi>Cereri, Phoeboque,</hi> patrique <hi>Lyaeo:</hi>
                  </note> To <hi>Ceres, Phaebus,</hi> and <hi>Lyaeus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And twenty harder names than <note n="*" place="margin">A figure ſo new, that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors have yet no name for't.</note> 
                  <hi>The' as.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Junoni ante omnes, cui vincla jugalia curae.</l>
                        <l>Ipſa tenens d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xtra pateram pulcherrima <hi>Dido,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But <hi>Juno</hi> had moſt veneration,</l>
               <l>As ſhe was Queen of copulation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Prayers being done, up <hi>Dido</hi> roſe,</l>
               <l>And to the Prieſt demurely goes;</l>
               <l>She gently pulls him by the garment,</l>
               <l>The reverend type of his preferment,</l>
               <l>And with moſt gracious looks and ſpeeches,</l>
               <l>To borrow a word or two beſeeches.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:65925:11"/>
               <l>The Prieſt bow'd low in Aukward wiſe,</l>
               <l>As 'tis you know Sir <hi>Roger</hi>'s guiſe,</l>
               <l>And in obſequious manner told her,</l>
               <l>Her Grace with him might make much bolder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Prieſt was held a mighty Clark,</l>
               <l>In myſteries profound and dark;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>——Spirantia conſulit exta.</hi>
                  </note> Had skill in Phyſick, and was able</l>
               <l>To tell folkes Fortunes by their Table.</l>
               <l>Him ſhe conjures, intreats, and prayes</l>
               <l>With all the cunning that ſhe has,</l>
               <l>Greaſes his fiſt; nay more engages,</l>
               <l>Thenceforth to mend his Quarters wages,</l>
               <l>If he would but reſolve the doubt</l>
               <l>That ſhe then came to him about.</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:65925:11"/>
               <l>But 't' had been vain, had he been wiſer</l>
               <l>Or to inſtruct, or to adviſe her,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Heu vatum ignare mentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> quid vota furentem,</l>
                        <l>Quid Delubra juvant? eſt mollis flamma medullas</l>
                        <l>Interea, &amp; tacitum vivit ſub pectore vulaus.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Alas! poor Prieſt! how fruitleſs is't</l>
               <l>To judge by Phyſnomy or Fiſt,</l>
               <l>Or what do Prophecies avail</l>
               <l>When women have a whisk i'th' tayle?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Uritur inſoelix Dido, toia<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> vagatur</l>
                        <l>Urbe furens.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dido</hi> for love in woful wife,</l>
               <l>Bubbles, and boyls, and broyls, and fries,</l>
               <l>And in her am'rous moods and tenſes,</l>
               <l>Even like one out of her ſenſes,</l>
               <l>About the Town ſhe runs and reels,</l>
               <l>VVith all the School-boys at her heels.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65925:12"/>
               <l>So have I ſeen in paſtures fair,</l>
               <l>VVhere Cattle educated are:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Qualis conject a cerva ſagitta,</l>
                        <l>Quam procul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> An heifer young when ſhe doth itch,</l>
               <l>VVith <hi>Gad breeze</hi> ſticking in her breech,</l>
               <l>From ſhady brake on ſuddain riſe,</l>
               <l>And with her tail erect to skies,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">—Illa fuga ſylvas ſaltuſque peragrat.</note> Run through the field with frisks and kicks</l>
               <l>In various capreolls and tricks.</l>
               <l>Some eaſe poor thing alaſs! to find;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">—Haeret lateri lethalis arundo.</note> VVhen loe the ſting ſticks faſt behind:</l>
               <l>One while ſhe takes her <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nunc media <hi>Aeneam</hi> ſecum per moenia ducit:</l>
                        <l>Sidoinaſque oſteatat opes, urbemque paratam.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> luſty lover,</l>
               <l>Meaning her paſſion to diſcover;</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65925:12"/>
               <l>She leads him out from place to place,</l>
               <l>And ſhows him all that ere ſhe has;</l>
               <l>Diſcloſes all her ſecret wealth,</l>
               <l>And ſayes, if <hi>Jove</hi> ſend life and health,</l>
               <l>That ſhe (though ſimple there ſhe ſtand)</l>
               <l>VVill make that Living as good land,</l>
               <l>If ſhe continue but a while on't,</l>
               <l>As any lies within five mile on't.</l>
               <l>Then ſhe <note n="k" place="margin">Incipit effari, mediaque in voce reſiſtit.</note> begins to mump and ſmatter,</l>
               <l>VVilling to break into the matter,</l>
               <l>And ask the queſtion when (alaſs!)</l>
               <l>To ſee how things will come to paſs!</l>
               <l>VVhen ſhe moſt fain her mind would break,</l>
               <l>She rather could have broke her neck</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65925:13"/>
               <l>Than ſpeak a word, vertue forſooth,</l>
               <l>And modeſty, ſo ſtopt her mouth.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin"> 
                     <hi>Nunc eadem labente die convivia quaerit:</hi>
                  </note> Over and over then ſhe treats</l>
               <l>Him, and his Mates, with ſundry meats,</l>
               <l>VVhileſt <hi>Trojans</hi> round beſiege her boards,</l>
               <l>Merry as <hi>Greeks,</hi> and drunk as Lords.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Iliacoſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> iterum demens audire labores</l>
                        <l>Expoſcit, pendet<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> iterum narrantis ab ore.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And ſure as ere they ſit to Table,</l>
               <l>She call's again to hear <hi>Troy</hi>'s Fable:</l>
               <l>Nay lov'd it ſo, that ſhe 'tis ſaid,</l>
               <l>The Ballad then of <hi>Troy</hi>-town made.</l>
               <l>VVe owe her for't, and let us pay't her;</l>
               <l>VVho Engliſht it, was her Tranſlator.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65925:13"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Poſt ubi digreſſi, lumenq<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> obſcura viciſſim</l>
                        <l>Luna, premit, ſuadent<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> cadentia ſydera ſomnos:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Now when with rakeing up the fire</l>
               <l>Each one departs to <hi>Bedford-ſhire:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And pillows all ſecurely ſnort on,</l>
               <l>Like Organiſts of fain'd <hi>Hogs-Norton;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sola domo moeret vacu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, ſtratiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> relictis</l>
                        <l>Incub at———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dido,</hi> poor Queen, alone doth lie,</l>
               <l>Dreaming on true-love's Phyſnomy:</l>
               <l>And in that humour ſhe the ſmall</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Aut gremio Aſcanium, genitoris imagine capta</l>
                        <l>Detinct, infandum ſi fallere poſſit amorem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aſcanius</hi> takes: <hi>Troy</hi>'s <hi>Juvenall;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in her lap on tuft of Sorrel,</l>
               <l>Laying the little wanton Gorrel,</l>
               <l>Oft would ſhe ſighing ſay, <hi>This Lad,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh that he were but like his Dad!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:65925:14"/>
               <l>This life the wofull <hi>Dido</hi> led,</l>
               <l>Eke at her board, and eke at bed,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non coeptae aſſurgunt turres: non arma juventus</l>
                        <l>Exercet, portuſve aut propugnacula bello</l>
                        <l>Tuta parant; Pendent opera interrupta, minae<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>
                        </l>
                        <l>Murorum ingentes, aequata<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> machina coelo.</l>
                        <l>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> ſimul ac tali perſenſit peſte teneri</l>
                        <l>Chdra Jovis conjux, nec famam obſtare furori;</l>
                        <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> aggreditur Venerem Saturnia d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ctis:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Her houſewifery no more regarding,</l>
               <l>Neither her ſpinning, nor her carding;</l>
               <l>But like a Dame of wits bereaven,</l>
               <l>Let all things go at ſix and ſeaven.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which when Queen <hi>Juno</hi> (for theſe two</l>
               <l>Were Clove and Orange, you muſt know)</l>
               <l>Perceiv'd, and that, then blind checks blinder,</l>
               <l>She threw all care and ſhame behind her,</l>
               <l>She <hi>Venus</hi> in theſe words accoaſts,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tu<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> puerque tuus: magnum &amp; memorabile nome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>Una dolo divum ſi ſoemina victa duorum eſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> You, and your ſon may make your boaſts,</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65925:14"/>
               <l>VVith ſhame enough, that God, and Goddeſs,</l>
               <l>Like ſublunary buſie-bodies,</l>
               <l>To make a woman light as feather</l>
               <l>Do lay your learned heads together.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nec me adeo fallit, veritam te moenia noſtra</l>
                        <l>Suſpectas habuiſſe domos Carthaginis altae.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 'Twas not for nought that I was ever</l>
               <l>Afraid of your two coming hither.</l>
               <l>You, and your little blinking Urchin</l>
               <l>Againſt this Town have ſtill been lurking;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Sed quis erit modus? aut quo nunc certamine tanto?</note> But when ſhall we give o're this puther</l>
               <l>And leave off vexing one another?</l>
               <l>Be thou but nice, I'le be thy friend,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quin potius pacem aeteraam, pactoſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> hymenaeos</l>
                        <l>Exercemus? habes tota quod mente petiſti.</l>
                        <l>Ardet amans Dido, traxit<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſa furorem;</l>
                        <l>Communem hunc ergo popu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um paribuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> regamus</l>
                        <l>Auſpiciis.————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Let's marry um, and there's an end.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:65925:15"/>
               <l>Thou haſt thy wiſh, thy little Archer</l>
               <l>Has made our <hi>Dido</hi> mad as March-hare.</l>
               <l>Then let us all old quarrels quitt,</l>
               <l>Leave being ſuch a peeviſh Titt:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—liceat Phrygio ſervire marito,</l>
                        <l>Dotaleſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tuae Tyrios permittere dextrae.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Troy</hi> Lads ſhall marry <hi>Tyrian</hi> Laſſes,</l>
               <l>And we will be as merry as paſſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Olli (ſenſit enim ſimulata mente locutam)</note> 
                  <hi>Venus</hi> who knew ſhe did but glaver,</l>
               <l>For all the fine ſmooth words ſhe gave her,</l>
               <l>And proffer'd love's not worth a Cow-turd,</l>
               <l>(You know) if ſpoke but from teeth outward,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Sic contra eſt ingreſſa Venus—</note> Like cunning Quean in ſmiles array'd her.</l>
               <l>And in her own coyn thus ſhe pay'd her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65925:15"/>
               <l>O <hi>Juno</hi> Queen, <hi>Jove</hi>'s Bedfellow,</l>
               <l>VVho here above, or who below,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Quis talia demens</l>
                        <l>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ua? aut tecum malit contendere bello?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> VVith thee would quarrel or contend,</l>
               <l>And not ſtill reſt thy loving friend?</l>
               <l>I like the motion well, but that</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Si modo quod memo as, factum fortuna ſequatur;</l>
                        <l>Sed fatis incerta feror; Ni Jupiter unam</l>
                        <l>Eſſe velit——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> There's one main thing I ſtumble at;</l>
               <l>And that in downright truth is this,</l>
               <l>(<hi>Jove</hi> pardon if I think amiſs,)</l>
               <l>I am afraid, (this doubt I put ye</l>
               <l>In deed-law now is ſomething ſmutty)</l>
               <l>But I the ſcruple muſt not ſmother;</l>
               <l>VVomen you know, to one another</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:65925:16"/>
               <l>May freely ſpeak) I (here bee't ſaid</l>
               <l>'Twixt you and mee) am ſore afraid,</l>
               <l>My ſon's ſo boyſterous, that he</l>
               <l>Perchance may wrong her Majeſty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Quam ſic excaepit Regia Juno,</l>
                        <l>Mecum erit iste labor:——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> At that Queen <hi>Juno</hi> ſmil'd, and ſaid;</l>
               <l>Of that (wench) never be afraid,</l>
               <l>For if they once come one to'th t'other,</l>
               <l>Shee'l ſcape as well as did her Mother:</l>
               <l>If then that <hi>Dido;</hi> and thy ſon,</l>
               <l>To do as other folks have done,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Nunc qua ratione, quod inſtat</l>
                        <l>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nfieri p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſit, paucis (adverte) docebo.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Thou give conſent: (mark) &amp; in few words</l>
               <l>VVich ſhal be friendly words &amp; true words;</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65925:16"/>
               <l>I'le tell thee how I've caſt about,</l>
               <l>And laid a plot to bring 'um to't.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Venatum Aeneas, unaque miſerrima <hi>Dido</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In nemus ire parant, ubi primos craſtinus ortus</l>
                        <l>Extuleri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Titan,</hi> radiiſque retexerit orbem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> To morrow ere the Sun (Heaven bleſs him)</l>
               <l>Can ſee to riſe, at leaſt to dreſs him.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> and the Queen have made,</l>
               <l>(The Queen and he I ſhould have ſaid)</l>
               <l>A match to go, after her wonting,</l>
               <l>Into the VVoods a Squirrel hunting:</l>
               <l>Now I, whilſt all on every ſide,</l>
               <l>The thickets round are occupide:</l>
               <l>And eagerly their Game are following,</l>
               <l>As hunters uſe, whooping and hollowing:</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65925:17"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>His ego nigrantem commiſta grandine nimbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>Dum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>repidant alae, ſaltuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> indagine cingunt,</l>
                        <l>Deſuper infundam—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> VVill cauſe big bellyed clouds to pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Upon their Coxcombs ſuch a ſhowre,</l>
               <l>And will with rain, and hail ſo clout 'um,</l>
               <l>They'ſt not have one dry thred about 'um.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">——&amp; toni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ru coelum omne ciebo.</note> Beſides ſuch thunder-claps ſhall burſt out,</l>
               <l>As ſome of um ſhall ſmell the worſe for't.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Diffugient comites, &amp; nocte tegen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur opaca.</note> 
                  <hi>Trojans</hi> and <hi>Tyrians</hi> helter-skelter,</l>
               <l>Will then all run to ſeek for ſhelter.</l>
               <l>Then each one there will ſhift for one,</l>
               <l>And leave the Queen and him alone.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Speluncam Dido, dux &amp; Trojanus candem</l>
                        <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>veni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt: adero, &amp; tua ſi mihi certa voluntas,</l>
                        <l>Connubio jungam, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dido</hi> and <hi>Bilbo</hi> in this caſe,</l>
               <l>Shall finde a Cave as fit a place</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:65925:17"/>
               <l>For ſuch an uſe, ſo fine and dark,</l>
               <l>That if <hi>Aeneas</hi> be a ſpark,</l>
               <l>They there in ſpite of all foul weather,</l>
               <l>May <hi>take a gentle touch</hi> together:</l>
               <l>So each of other may have proof,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—ſtabili, propriam<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dicabo;</l>
                        <l>Hic Hymenaeus erit.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And marry after, time enough.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> who very well could fadom</l>
               <l>The bottom of this ſubtle Maddam,</l>
               <l>Soon ſmelt her practice, art and plott,</l>
               <l>(For you muſt know the ſent was hott)</l>
               <l>Yet that ſhe might her malice blind,</l>
               <l>And fit the Lady in her kinde,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Non adverſata petenti</l>
                        <l>Annuit, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dolis riſit Cytheraea repertis.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> She ſeems her free conſent to give,</l>
               <l>And trips it, laughing in her ſleeve.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:65925:18"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Oceanum interea ſurgens aurora reliquit:</l>
                        <l>It portis jubare exerto delecta juvent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>:</l>
                        <l>Retia rara, plag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Mean while the Sun as it his courſe is,</l>
               <l>Got up to dreſs and water's Horſes;</l>
               <l>VVhen out the merry Hunters come,</l>
               <l>VVith them a fellow with a Drumme<note n="*" place="margin">A very neceſſary inſtrument in Squir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note>,</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Tyrian</hi> Squirrels will not budg elſe,</l>
               <l>Well arm'd they were <note n="n" place="margin">—Lato venabula ferro,</note> with ſtaves and cudgels,</l>
               <l>Tykes too they had of all ſorts,<note n="o" place="margin">———Et od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a canum vis.</note> Bandogs,</l>
               <l>Cuts, Spaniels, Water-dogs, and Land-dogs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Reginam thalamo cunctantem, ad limina primi</l>
                        <l>Poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>orum expectant.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Theſe for the Queen expecting tarry,</l>
               <l>VVho longer lay than ordinary;</l>
               <l>For ſhe at night could take no eaſe,</l>
               <l>She had been bit ſo ſore with Fleas.</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:65925:18"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Oſtroque inſignis &amp; auro</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>at ſonipes, ac fraena ferox ſpumantia mandit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Her Mare well trapt of her own ſpinning,</l>
               <l>Ty'd to the pales ſtood likewiſe whinnying;</l>
               <l>For why (as Poets ſing the Fable)</l>
               <l>Her foal was bolted up i'th' Stable.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Tandem progreditur.</note> At laſt ſhe ſallies from the Houſe,</l>
               <l>As fine and brisk as body louſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Sid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niam picto chlamydem circumdata lymbo,</note> She Hood and Safeguard had bran new,</l>
               <l>The lace was yellow, cloth was blew:</l>
               <l>Faſt to her girdle, ty'd with thong,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cui pharetra ex auro——</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>urea purpuream ſubnectit fibula veſtem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> A bunch of Keyes compleatly hung:</l>
               <l>For why well knew the thriſty Queen,</l>
               <l>That Servants ſtill have ſlippery been:</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:65925:19"/>
               <l>Which made her carefull of her pelf</l>
               <l>Evermore keep her Keyes her ſelf.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">———<hi>et lae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Jülus.</hi>
                  </note> With her <hi>Jülus</hi> came, that ſtripling,</l>
               <l>A youth een ſpoyl'd for want of whipping;</l>
               <l>For's Father and his fooliſh Granam</l>
               <l>Had ever made a wanton to him:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——ipſe ante alios pulcherrimus omnes</l>
                        <l>Infert ſe ſocium Aeneas—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But when his Sire appear'd in play,</l>
               <l>Mounted upon his Galloway,</l>
               <l>'Tis ſaid by ſome that better knew him,</l>
               <l>The reſt look't like Tooth-drawers to him:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Qualis ubi hybernam Lyciam, Xanthi<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> fluenta</l>
                        <l>Deſerit, ac Delum maternum inviſit Apollo,</l>
                        <l>Inſtaura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> choros:—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> No ſprightly Groom ſo trim and trick is,</l>
               <l>That juſt upon preferments prick is,</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:65925:19"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Mollique fluentem</l>
                        <l>Fronde premit crinem fingens atque implicat auro:</l>
                        <l>——Haud illo ſegnior ibat</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aeneas,</hi> tantum egregio decus enilet ore.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> As was <hi>Aeneas,</hi> ſtories ſay,</l>
               <l>When clad in cloaths of Holy-day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His breeches ſav'd from <hi>Troys</hi> combuſtion</l>
               <l>Were Kendal, and his Doublet Fuſtian;</l>
               <l>Pinck't with moſt admirable grace,</l>
               <l>And richly laid with green-ſilk-lace.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Tela ſonant humeris——</note> Athwart his brawny ſhoulders came</l>
               <l>A Bauldrick made, and trim'd with' ſame;</l>
               <l>Where Twibil hung with basket hilt,</l>
               <l>Grown ruſty now, but had been gilt:</l>
               <l>Or guilty elſe of many a thwack,</l>
               <l>With dudgeon Dagger at his back.</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:65925:20"/>
               <l>Upon his head, he wore a hat,</l>
               <l>Inſtead of Sattin fac'd with fat,</l>
               <l>Which being limber-grown, we find</l>
               <l>Moſt ſwaſhingly pin'd up behind;</l>
               <l>With brooch as gawdy, and as tall,</l>
               <l>As very foremoſt horſe of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In beſt apparel thus aray'd,</l>
               <l>They now begin their Cavalcade</l>
               <l>Towards the woods, <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Poſtquam altos ventum in montes, atque iavia ſaxa,</l>
                        <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ce ſerae ſaxi dejectae vertice—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> where being ere long</l>
               <l>Arriv'd (for 'twas not paſt a furlong</l>
               <l>From <hi>Carthage,</hi> as the learned compute it,</l>
               <l>And let who has been there confute it)</l>
               <l>They every way diſperſe themſelves,</l>
               <l>To watch the little nimble Elves;</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65925:20"/>
               <l>As who ſhould ſay, Come this, or that way,</l>
               <l>T'other, or any way, have at ye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Drummer now 'gan lay about him,</l>
               <l>And all the people fall a ſhouting,</l>
               <l>Such peals they gave of men, and boyes,</l>
               <l>A man could hardly hear for noyſe;</l>
               <l>Nay <hi>Dido</hi> Queen, they ſwore that heard it,</l>
               <l>Shouted as loud as any there did.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Decurrere jugis; alia de parte patentes</l>
                        <l>Tranſmittunt cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſu campos, atque agmina Sq (cervi) lls</l>
                        <l>Pulvetulenta ſuga, glomerant, montem<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> relinquunt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> The frighted Squirrel's ſtumps belabour</l>
               <l>As they had danc't to Pipe and Tabour;</l>
               <l>Skipping and leaping in their dances</l>
               <l>From tree to tree, ore boughs and branches,</l>
               <l>Now on the utmoſt top, and then,</l>
               <l>At one leap at the root again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:65925:21"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>At puer <hi>Aſcanius</hi> mediis in vallibus acri</l>
                        <l>Gaudet equo; jamque hos curſu, jam praeterit ilbos:</l>
                        <l>Spumantemque dari (pecora inter in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r ia) vatis</l>
                        <l>Optat aprum, aut ſulvum deſcendere monte l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>onem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But young <hi>Aſcanius</hi> hops o'th' houſe,</l>
               <l>Car'd not for Squirrelling a louſe;</l>
               <l>For he's, whilſt they are at their chace,</l>
               <l>Playing at <hi>hide and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k,</hi> or <hi>Baſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Among his mates, and wiſhes rather,</l>
               <l>(And ſo the Stripling told his Father,)</l>
               <l>For naughty Vermine, that would bite him,</l>
               <l>Or Throſtle neaſt, though't did—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Intera magno miſceri murmure coelwn</l>
                        <l>Incipit:——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Mean while the clouds began to clatter,</l>
               <l>And to poure down whole pailes of water,</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65925:21"/>
               <l>The thunder quite outroar'd the drum,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Inſequitur comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſta grandine nimbus,</l>
                        <l>Et <hi>Tyrii</hi> comites paſſim, &amp; <hi>Trojana</hi> juventus,</l>
                        <l>D <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>daniuſque nepos Veneris, diverſa per agros</l>
                        <l>Tecta metu petiere; ruunt de montibus amnes.</l>
                        <l>———ſulſere ignes——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And hail ſtones bigger than ones thumb</l>
               <l>Came pelting down. Then all to ſave 'um,</l>
               <l>Ran as if twenty Devils drave 'um.</l>
               <l>Whilſt young <hi>Aſcanius,</hi> and his mates,</l>
               <l>Were waſht and daſht like water-Rats.</l>
               <l>Fair <hi>Dido</hi> then for all her whoops,</l>
               <l>Bang'd her old Mare about the ſtoops,</l>
               <l>And jogg'd her buttocks, though a Queen,</l>
               <l>For fear of being wet to th' skin;</l>
               <l>Nay even <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſelf, forgetting</l>
               <l>His reputation. ſhruncke i'th' wetting,</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:65925:22"/>
               <l>And ran, or would have done at leaſt,</l>
               <l>But that his Horſe, a ſober beaſt,</l>
               <l>Proceeded ſlow, with motion grave,</l>
               <l>And crav'd the ſpurre, in care to ſave</l>
               <l>His Maſters neck, as ſome ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>Though his care was to ſave his cloaths.</l>
               <l>He ſpurr'd; nor yet was <hi>Dido</hi> idle,</l>
               <l>For gingle, gingle went her bridle,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Speluucam <hi>Dido,</hi> dux &amp; <hi>Trojanus</hi> eandem</l>
                        <l>Deveniunt; prima &amp; Tellus &amp; pronuba <hi>Juno</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Dant ſignum——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Till Fortune, or Dame <hi>Juno</hi> rather,</l>
               <l>Clapt 'um into a Cave together.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Cave ſo darkſome was, that I do</l>
               <l>Think <hi>Joan</hi> had been as good as <hi>Dido:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But ſo it was, in that hole they</l>
               <l>Grew intimate as one may ſay:</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:65925:22"/>
               <l>The Queen was blith as bird in tree,</l>
               <l>And bill'd as wantonly, whilſt hee</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———Conſcius aether</l>
                        <l>Conjugii————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> By hinlock ſeazing faſt occaſion,</l>
               <l>Slipt into <hi>Dido</hi>'s converſation:</l>
               <l>And in that very place and ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>'Tis thought <hi>Aeneas</hi> did her reaſon,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Illa dies primus lethi, primuſque malorum</l>
                        <l>canſa fuit.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> This ſport of miſchief much was cauſe,</l>
               <l>For ſweet-meat will have ſowre ſauce;</l>
               <l>And there their time in Cave ſo ſpending,</l>
               <l>Beginning was of <hi>Dido</hi>'s ending.</l>
               <l>Her Majeſty now no more nice is;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Neque enim ſpeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſamave movetur,</l>
                        <l>Nec jam furtivum <hi>Dido</hi> meditatur amorem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Nor ſeeks ſhe now by fine devices,</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:65925:23"/>
               <l>To hide her ſhame, but leads a life,</l>
               <l>As if they had been<note n="l" place="margin">Conjugium vocat, hoc praetexit nomine culpam.</note> man and wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Extemplo <hi>Lybiae</hi> magnas it fama per urbes:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fama</hi>————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> At this a wench call'd <hi>Fame</hi> flew out</l>
               <l>To all the good-Towns round about.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Fame</hi> was daughter to a Cryer,</l>
               <l>That whilome liv'd in Carthage-Shire,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Parva metu primo, mox ſeſe attollit in auras:</l>
                        <l>Ingreditur<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſolo, &amp; caput inter nubila condit.</l>
                        <l>Mobilitate viget, vireſque acquirit euade.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> A little prating ſlut, no higher,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Dido</hi> firſt arriv'd at <hi>Tyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Than this—But in a few years ſpace</l>
               <l>Grown up a luſty ſtrapping laſs.</l>
               <l>A long and laſie quean I ween</l>
               <l>She was, brought up to ſow, nor ſpin,</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65925:23"/>
               <l>Nor any kind of Houſewifery,</l>
               <l>To get an honeſt living by;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Pedibus celerem, &amp; pernicibus alis:</l>
                        <l>Cui tot vigiles oculi———</l>
                        <l>Tot linguae, lotidem ora ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nant, tot, ſubrigit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ures.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But ſauntred idely up and down,</l>
               <l>From houſe to houſe, and town to town;</l>
               <l>To ſpie and liſten after news</l>
               <l>Which ſhe ſo miſchievouſly brews;</l>
               <l>That ſtill what ere ſhe ſees or hears,</l>
               <l>Sets folks together by the ears.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Monſtrum horrendum, ingens—</note> This baggage that ſtill took a pride to</l>
               <l>Slander and back-bite poor Queen <hi>Dido;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Becauſe the Queen once on detection,</l>
               <l>Sent her to th' Manſion of Correction.</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:65925:24"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Haec tum multiplici populos ſermone replebat,</l>
                        <l>Gaudens,———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Glad ſhe had got this tale by th' end,</l>
               <l>Runs me about to foe and friend;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Veniſſe <hi>Aeneam Trojano</hi> a ſanguine cretum:</l>
                        <l>Cui ſe palchra viro dignetur jungere <hi>Dido.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nunc hyemem inter ſe luxu, quam longa, fovere,</l>
                        <l>Regnorum imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>res, tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pique cupidine captos.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And tells 'um that a fellow came</l>
               <l>From <hi>Troy,</hi> or ſuch a kind of Name,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Tyre,</hi> about a fortnight ſince,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Dido</hi> feaſted like a Prince:</l>
               <l>Was with her alwayes, day and night,</l>
               <l>Nor could endure him from her ſight,</l>
               <l>And that 'twas thought ſhe meant to marry him:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Haec paſſim deafaeda virum diffundit in ora.</note> At this rate talkt the foul-mouth'd car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion!</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65925:24"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Protinus ad regem curſus det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rquet <hi>Iarbam:</hi>
                  </note> At laſt ſhe does t' <hi>Iarbas</hi> goe,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Fama malum quo non aliud velocius ullum.</l>
                        <l>Hie Ammone ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us.———</l>
                        <l>Cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um aras poſuit——</l>
                        <l>———Pecudumque cruore</l>
                        <l>Pingue ſolum &amp; variis florentia limina ſertis.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> She never in ſuch things was ſlow,</l>
               <l>And tells him all. Now this <hi>Iarbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>Dido</hi>'s love was in a hard-caſe,</l>
               <l>And had been long. Oft did he woe her,</l>
               <l>And did the beſt he could do to her:</l>
               <l>But ſtill in vain he broke his mind,</l>
               <l>'Twas throwing ſtones againſt the wind;</l>
               <l>For though ſhe wiſe and wealthy knew him,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dido</hi> had nothing to ſay to him.</l>
               <l>'Tis true, the field he had great flocks on,</l>
               <l>Sheep, Goats, and Cowes, Horſes and Oxen;</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:65925:25"/>
               <l>With money ſtore, and other riches;</l>
               <l>But one fowl flaw he had in's breeches</l>
               <l>That ſpoil'd all; For ſhe had heard the thing,</l>
               <l>One time, as ſhe was Goſſiping:</l>
               <l>As in ſuch matters, while you live,</l>
               <l>Women will be inquiſitive:</l>
               <l>Which was that he (as ſtory tells)</l>
               <l>A Rupture had, or ſomewhat elſe:</l>
               <l>But 'twas enough to make her hate him,</l>
               <l>Nay even as 'twere abominate him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When fame had told him of the <hi>Trojan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Iſque amens animi, &amp; rumore accenſus amaro.</note> 
                  <hi>Iarbas</hi> took it in ſuch dudgeon,</l>
               <l>Such high abuſe, and evil part,</l>
               <l>He almoſt could have found in's heart,</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65925:25"/>
               <l>T'have tane his knife or elſe his Hanger,</l>
               <l>But yet the man had wit in's anger:</l>
               <l>And ſince to curſe it was no boot,</l>
               <l>He'd try if praying would not doo't;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Dicitur ante aras——</l>
                        <l>Multa Jovem manibus ſupplex oraſſe ſupinis:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And therefore thus in heavy chear,</l>
               <l>Made his caſe known to <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Jupiter omnipotens, cui nunc Mauruſia pictis</l>
                        <l>Gens epulata toris Lenae um libat honorem,</l>
                        <l>Aſpicis haec? an te genitor cum fulmina torques,</l>
                        <l>Nequicquam horremus?——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> O <hi>Jupiter</hi> moſt great and able,</l>
               <l>Whoſe health I every day at Table,</l>
               <l>Drink once or twice! Doſt thou (O where is</l>
               <l>Thy ſight!) not ſee, what doings here is!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Caecique in nubibus ignes</l>
                        <l>Terrificant animos——</l>
                        <l>—Et inania murmura miſcent?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Shall we when thou thunderſt, doſt think,</l>
               <l>So as to ſowre all our drink;</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:65925:26"/>
               <l>And when the clouds in ſtormes do burſt,</l>
               <l>Not care, but did thee do thy worſt!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Foemina, quae noſtris errans in finibus—</note> A Wandring woman that had ſcarce</l>
               <l>A rag to hang upon her—</l>
               <l>When ſhe came hither firſt; and would</l>
               <l>Have then been glad to work for food:</l>
               <l>Is now forſooth, ſo proud (what elſe!)</l>
               <l>And ſtands ſo on her pantables,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Connubia noſtra</l>
                        <l>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ppulit, ac dominum <hi>Aeneam</hi> in r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gna recepit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> That ſhe has ſaid me nay moſt ſlightly,</l>
               <l>And (on the very nonce to ſpite me)</l>
               <l>Has marry'd a ſpruce youth they ſay,</l>
               <l>(Whom ſome ill wind ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that away)</l>
               <l>One ſquire <hi>Aeneas,</hi> a great Kelf,</l>
               <l>Some wandring hang-man like her ſelf:</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:65925:26"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Et nunc ille Paris——</l>
                        <l>——Rapto potitur: nos munera templis</l>
                        <l>Quippe tuis ferimus, famamque ſovennus inanem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And now this Swabber, by the maskins,</l>
               <l>Has <hi>Dido</hi> by the Gally-Gaskins,</l>
               <l>VVhilſt I (for ſtill thou deafiſh art too't)</l>
               <l>May pray, and pray, and pray my heart out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Talibus orantem dictis, araſque tenentem</l>
                        <l>Audiit omnipotens; oculoſque ad moe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ia torſit</l>
                        <l>Regia, &amp; oblitos famae mclioris amantes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Thus wofully <hi>Iarbas</hi> pray'd:</l>
               <l>VVhilſt <hi>Jove</hi> heard every word he ſaid;</l>
               <l>And turning ſtraight his eyes to <hi>Tyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To look for <hi>Dido,</hi> and her ſquire,</l>
               <l>All in a Chamber finely matted,</l>
               <l>He very fairly ſpide 'um ſquatted.</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:65925:27"/>
               <l>At which as 'twere, ſomewhat in fury,</l>
               <l>He calls his nimble youth <hi>Mercury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thus beſpake him, Sirrha hear ye,</l>
               <l>Put on the wings that uſe to bear ye,</l>
               <l>Away to <hi>Carthage;</hi> there's a ſtranger,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Trojan</hi> lies at rack and manger:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non illum nobis genitrix pulcherrima talem.</l>
                        <l>Promiſit———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Tell him from me that his ſmug Mother,</l>
               <l>Did paſs her word that he another</l>
               <l>Manner of life and converſation</l>
               <l>Should lead, and leave this occupation.<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tunc ſic <hi>Mercurium</hi> alloquitur, ac talia mandat,</l>
                        <l>Vade, age, nate, voca <hi>Zephyros,</hi> &amp; labere pennis</l>
                        <l>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>daniumque ducem, <hi>Tyria Carthagine</hi> qui nunc</l>
                        <l>Expectat———</l>
                        <l>Alloquere, &amp; celeres deſer mea dicta per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>as.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:65925:27"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">—<hi>Graiumque ideo bis vindicat armis.</hi>
                  </note> Or twice the <hi>Graecian</hi> Cavaleers</l>
               <l>Had beaten's brains about his ears,</l>
               <l>Ere this: and tell him more <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sed fore qui graviddm imperiis belloque frementem</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Italiam</hi> regeret, genus alto a ſanguine Teucri</l>
                        <l>Proderet, et totum ſub leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s mitteret orbem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> that he,</l>
               <l>Who means to conquer <hi>Italy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Muſt with his work goe through ſtitches,</l>
               <l>And not run hunting after bitches:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Si nulla accendit tantarum gloria rerum,</l>
                        <l>Nec ſuper ipſe ſuâ molitur laude laborem,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But if he will not venture's pate.</l>
               <l>A rap or too for an Eſtate,</l>
               <l>As by his prancks it doth appear,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Aſcanione pater <hi>Romanas</hi> invidit arces,</l>
                        <l>Nec prolem A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſoniam, et Laviaia reſpicit arva?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Methinks though he might do'r for's heir.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:65925:28"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Quid ſtruit? aut qua ſpe inimica in gente moratur?</note> Ask what the Devil 'tis he means,</l>
               <l>To ſpend his time thus among queans:</l>
               <l>Not minding miſchiefs, nor miſhaps;</l>
               <l>Nor fearing <hi>Dido</hi>'s after-claps.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Naviget: haec ſumma eſt, hic noſtri nuncius eſto.</note> Bid him be trudging he were beſt;</l>
               <l>If I come to him, I proteſt,</l>
               <l>I'le ſend him packing elſe ſuch new-wayes,</l>
               <l>He ſhall remember me theſe two-dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Dixcrat. Ille patris magni parere parabat</l>
                        <l>Imperio———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> This ſaid, <hi>Jove</hi> need not bid him twice,</l>
               <l>Away he trips it in a trice,</l>
               <l>To make him ready to be gone:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Et primum pedibus talaria nectit</l>
                        <l>Aurea: quae ſublimem alis ſive aequora ſupra,</l>
                        <l>Seu terram, rapido pariter cum flamine portant.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And firſt his pumps he faſtned on;</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:65925:28"/>
               <l>Which being neatly pinckt and cut,</l>
               <l>And finely fitted to his foot:</l>
               <l>Had wings tyde on with thongs of leather,</l>
               <l>Or Taching ends, I know not whether.</l>
               <l>Which he could flie withall as well,</l>
               <l>As he'd been brought up too't from th' ſhell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tum virgam capit; hac animas ille evocat Orco</l>
                        <l>Pallentes, alias ſub triſtia <hi>Tartara</hi> mittit,</l>
                        <l>Dat ſomnos adimitque, &amp; lumina morte reſignat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Then in his hand he takes a thick Bat,</l>
               <l>With which he us'd to play at Kit cat;</l>
               <l>To beat mens Apples from their trees,</l>
               <l>With twenty other rogueries;</l>
               <l>Beſides (as Rake-hells will abuſe dayes)</l>
               <l>To throw at Cocks upon <hi>Shrove-Tueſdayes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:65925:29"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſretus agit ventos, et turbida tranat</l>
                        <l>Nubila——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Thus dight he like a Partridge ſprings</l>
               <l>Cutting the ayre with nimble wings:</l>
               <l>'Twas well his care had tyde um faſt,</l>
               <l>Elſe ten to one hee'd flowne his laſt:</l>
               <l>No Swallow could have overgone him,</l>
               <l>He flew as if a Hawk had flowne him,</l>
               <l>Untill he ſaw a very high-Hill,</l>
               <l>A higher Hill by farre then my Hill;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Jamque volans apicem, et latera ardua cernit</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Atlantis</hi> duri,——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Attlas</hi> 'twas call'd; So high a one</l>
               <l>That Pen-men-Maure's, a cherry-ſtone</l>
               <l>Compar'd: you could not thruſt a knife</l>
               <l>'Twixt Heaven and it, to ſave your Life;</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:65925:29"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">——Caelum qui vertice ſulcit.</note> It props the skye, as <hi>Virgil</hi> marks,</l>
               <l>Or elſe 'tis thought we ſhould have larks:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Hic primum paribus nitens <hi>Cyllenius</hi> alis Conſtitit:</note> Here firſt did <hi>Mercury</hi> alight,</l>
               <l>To bait, and reſt him after's flight;</l>
               <l>Where having prun'd his heeles a little</l>
               <l>And ſmooth'd his Plumes with <note n="*" place="margin">Tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd he did that before he bayted.</note> faſting ſpittle</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">—Huic toto praeceps ſe corpore ad undas Miſit—;</note> From thence he took another freak</l>
               <l>As if he meant to break his neck.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>vi ſimilis quae circum littora circum</l>
                        <l>Piſcoſos ſcopulos humilis volat aequora juxta:</l>
                        <l>Haud aliter terras inter, caelumque volabat</l>
                        <l>Littus arenoſum <hi>Lybiae,</hi> ventoſque ſecabat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Even as a Hawk her ſelf doth carry</l>
               <l>From kill-ducks place to ſtoope her quarry:</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:65925:30"/>
               <l>So <hi>Mercury</hi> to mortal view,</l>
               <l>Himſelf from <hi>Atlas</hi> head-long threw.</l>
               <l>Stones caſt by fam'd <hi>Pariſian</hi> ſlinger,</l>
               <l>Compar'd to him, would ſeem to linger;</l>
               <l>And Arrows looſt from <hi>Gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b-ſtreet</hi> bow</l>
               <l>In <hi>Finsbury,</hi> to him are ſlow:</l>
               <l>Nay Lightning darted from above,</l>
               <l>With flaming tail from angry <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Would in compariſon appear,</l>
               <l>To creep like lazie loyterer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>In primum alatis tetigit Magnalia plantis;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aeneam</hi> fundantem arces, ac tecta novantem</l>
                        <l>Conſpicit:———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> The firſt place after this vagary,</l>
               <l>He lighted on, was <hi>Dido</hi>'s dayry;</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:65925:30"/>
               <l>Whence he <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſoon did ſpy,</l>
               <l>Ord'ring her Highneſs husbandry:</l>
               <l>He took upon him as her Spouſe,</l>
               <l>And vapour'd like the man o'th' houſe;</l>
               <l>For all that time, as't came to paſs,</l>
               <l>In quarrel high engag'd he was,</l>
               <l>And ready in his fumigation</l>
               <l>(As Hiſtories do make relation)</l>
               <l>To fall to logger-heads, as't appears,</l>
               <l>With a few ſaucy Carpenters:</l>
               <l>Who building were a houſe of eaſe,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Dido</hi> in Neceſſities:</l>
               <l>They would not follow his advice</l>
               <l>(As work-men ſtill are over-wiſe)</l>
               <l>VVhich made him foame, and flirt out ſpittle,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they made the holes too little.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:65925:31"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Illi ſtellatus jaſpide ſalva</l>
                        <l>Enſis erat———.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Down hanging by his ſide he had,</l>
               <l>A dangerous bright-browne flaſhing blade,</l>
               <l>'T had beene new furbuſht up at <hi>Tyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A better never paſt the fire.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———Tyrioque ardebat murice Laena</l>
                        <l>Demiſſa ex humeris: Dives qnae munera Dido</l>
                        <l>Fecerat, et ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i telas diſcreverat auro.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> A Jacket on his back he wore,</l>
               <l>Lin'd through, and through with Cony Fur,</l>
               <l>Given as a preſent by the Queen:</l>
               <l>It had indeed her Husband's been;</l>
               <l>But neither by the Nap, nor tearing</l>
               <l>Was it a pin the worſe for wearing.</l>
               <l>This (as of either Queene, or King</l>
               <l>Vile people will be cenſuring)</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65925:31"/>
               <l>Was given <hi>Aeneas</hi> for a charme,</l>
               <l>And though the Queen might think no harm;</l>
               <l>Yet ſome have giv'n a parlous hint,</l>
               <l>Of a ſtrange hidden vertue in't.</l>
               <l>Ecquip't thus fine <hi>Mercury</hi> found him,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Continuo invadit: tu nunc <hi>Carthaginis</hi> altae</l>
                        <l>Fundamenta locas, pulchramque uxoribus urbem</l>
                        <l>Extruis, (heu!) regni rerumque oblite tuarum.</l>
                        <l>Ipſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ûm tibi me claro demi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tit Olympo</l>
                        <l>Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ator coelum, &amp; terras qui numine torquet.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And roundly in his ear thus round him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou here thy ſelf moſt buſie makes,</l>
               <l>In building for the Queen a Jakes;</l>
               <l>But never think'ſt, ſuch is thy wiſeneſs,</l>
               <l>What ſhall become of thy own buſineſs:</l>
               <l>The thunder-thumper who by threaves,</l>
               <l>Makes men to quake like Aſpen-leaves;</l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:65925:32"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ipſe haec ferre jubet celeres mandata per auras,</l>
                        <l>Quid ſtruis? aut quâ ſpe Lybicis teris otia terris?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> He whom the reſt o'th' Gods do honour,</l>
               <l>Has ſent me from <hi>Olympus</hi> Mannor,</l>
               <l>To ask thee what thou do'ſt intend,</l>
               <l>Thy time thus wickedly to ſpend;</l>
               <l>And loyter here like a Hum-drum,</l>
               <l>Not caring what thou doſt, nor whom.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Si te nulla movet tantarum gloria rerum</l>
                        <l>Nec ſuper ipſe tuâ—&amp;c.—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> He ſayes, though fearful, as a ſtranger,</l>
               <l>Thy cox-comb thou'lt not bring in danger</l>
               <l>To mend thy ſtate, nor get thy living</l>
               <l>By any honeſt way of thriving:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Aſcanium ſurgentem, &amp; ſpes haeredis Jüli</l>
                        <l>Reſpice: cui regnum Italiae, Romana<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tellus</l>
                        <l>Dehentur.—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> He thinks though thou might'ſt take ſome care</l>
               <l>Of him that is thy Son and Heir,</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:65925:32"/>
               <l>And not thraſh here like Bore unworthy</l>
               <l>VVhen he has made proviſion for thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Tali Cyllenius ore locutus.</l>
                        <l>Mortales viſus medio ſermone reliqut,</l>
                        <l>Et procul in tenuem ex oculis evanuit auram.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> vaniſht having ſpoke as</l>
               <l>Y'ave heard like any <hi>Hocus-Pocus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And home-ward did forthwith aſpire,</l>
               <l>Nor ever ſtay'd to drink at <hi>Tyre.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>At vero Aeneas aſpectu obmutuit amens,</l>
                        <l>Arrectae<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> borrore comae, &amp; vox ſaucibus haeſit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But <hi>Don Aeneas</hi> at the viſion</l>
               <l>VVas in a very ſad condition;</l>
               <l>He could not ſpeak to Foe or Friend,</l>
               <l>And eke his Hair did ſtand on end</l>
               <l>So ſtiff, it thruſt his Hat ſo far</l>
               <l>Above his Head into the air,</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:65925:33"/>
               <l>That a great Turky might have flown,</l>
               <l>Betwixt his Bonnet and his Crown.</l>
               <l>Half frighted out on's little wit;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Ardet abire fuga———</note> He now had eggs (I faith) o'th' ſpit,</l>
               <l>'Till he was gone:<note n="k" place="margin">Heu! quid agat?———</note> But how (alaſs!)</l>
               <l>To break the matter to her Grace,</l>
               <l>He knew no more, the baſhful Groom,</l>
               <l>Than did the furtheſt man of <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Quo nunc Reginam ambire furentem</l>
                        <l>Audeat affatu? &amp; quae prima exordia ſumat?</l>
                        <l>Atque animum nunc huc celerem, nunc dividit illuc,</l>
                        <l>In parteſque rapit varias——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Nor could he frame him to begin,</l>
               <l>T' appeaſe that loving ſoul the Queen:</l>
               <l>For nought more vexes Womens bloods,</l>
               <l>Than to be left ſo in the ſuds.</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:65925:33"/>
               <l>In this quandary ſcratching's pate,</l>
               <l>After a penſive long debate</l>
               <l>He calls at laſt his fellow Rake-hells,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Claſſem aptent taciti, ſocios ad littora cogant,</l>
                        <l>Anna parent,———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And bid's um get their tools, and tackles,</l>
               <l>Aboard their wherries, and be heedful,</l>
               <l>To lay in all things that were needful,</l>
               <l>Eſpecially meat:<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Et quae ſit rebus cauſa novandis,</l>
                        <l>Diſſimulent: quando interca optima Dido</l>
                        <l>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ciat.————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> but ſtowe it,</l>
               <l>So ſecretly that none might know it;</l>
               <l>That on occaſion in a trice Sir</l>
               <l>They might be gone, and none the wiſer;</l>
               <l>And ſince he humbly did conceive,</l>
               <l>To ſteale away, and take no leave,</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:65925:34"/>
               <l>VVould be uncivil, and enough</l>
               <l>To tear a heart though made of Buffe:</l>
               <l>He was reſolv'd to take the Queen,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Et quae molliſſima fandi</l>
                        <l>Tempora, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> modus.—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> VVhen ſet upon ſome merry pin,</l>
               <l>And tell her plain with vows moſt fervent,</l>
               <l>He was her Graces humble Servant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">At Regina dolos (quis fallere poſſit amantem?)</note> But <hi>Dido Carthage</hi> Queen (for who</l>
               <l>Can think to cheat a woman ſo?)</l>
               <l>VVas ſoon, I warrant you, aware</l>
               <l>O'th' ſlippery trick he meant to play her.</l>
               <l>'Tis true ſhe ever had been jealous</l>
               <l>Of all ſuch vagrant kind of fellows,</l>
               <l>And kept her things ſafe under lock,</l>
               <l>Ere ſince the ſtealing of her Smock:</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:65925:34"/>
               <l>But now to adde unto her fear,</l>
               <l>She had it buzz'd into her ear</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Praeſenſit, motuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> excepit prima futuros,</l>
                        <l>Ownia tuta timens.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> By that miſchievous prating VVhore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fame,</hi> that I told you of before;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Eadem impia fama furenti</l>
                        <l>Detulit.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Not as they ſay out of good will,</l>
               <l>But to be brewing miſchief ſtill,</l>
               <l>That he for all his fair pretences</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">———Armari claſſem, curſum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> parari.</note> Had greas'd his Boots and waſht his Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</l>
               <l>And now was ready ſet on wheels,</l>
               <l>To ſhew a nimble pair of heels.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Saevit inops animi; totam<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> incenſa per urbem</l>
                        <l>Bacchatur———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> This ſudden news, I do aſſure yee,</l>
               <l>Put <hi>Dido</hi> in a deſp'rate fury,</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65925:35"/>
               <l>And made her frisk about and gad,</l>
               <l>That all her people thought her mad;</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſhe from houſe to houſe did flie,</l>
               <l>As ſhe had run with hue and crie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Qualis commotis excita ſacris</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thyas,</hi> ubi audilo ſtimulant Trieterica <hi>Baccho</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Orgia, nocturnuſque vocat clamore Cythaeren.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Even as a Philly never ridden,</l>
               <l>When by the Jocky firſt beſtridden,</l>
               <l>If naughty boy do thruſt a nettle</l>
               <l>Under her Dock, to try her mettle,</l>
               <l>Does riſe and plunge, curvet and kick,</l>
               <l>Enough to break her riders neck;</l>
               <l>Even ſo Queen <hi>Dido</hi> at that tide,</l>
               <l>Laying all Majeſty aſide,</l>
               <l>Play'd ſuch mad freaks, that well were they</l>
               <l>Could furtheſt get out of her way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:65925:35"/>
               <l>Thus flinging round from place to place,</l>
               <l>At laſt to make it ſhort, her Grace</l>
               <l>Finds me amongſt a crew of Mad-Gaps,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> at one Mother <hi>Red-Caps.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well overtane (quoth ſhe) half weeping,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Tandem his <hi>Aeneam</hi> compellat vocibus ull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>;</note> 
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> thour't a pretious Pepin,</l>
               <l>To think to ſteal ſo ſlily from me,</l>
               <l>When thou haſt had thy foul will o' me.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Diſſimulare etiam ſper aſti perfide, tantum</l>
                        <l>Poſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſas? tacituſque meâ decedere terrâ,</l>
                        <l>Nec te noſter amor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ee te data dextera quondant</l>
                        <l>—Tenet?——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Could not my Love (thou knave) have ſtay'd thee;</l>
               <l>Nor yet the promiſe thou haſt made mee;</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:65925:36"/>
               <l>Nor that thou knowſt if thou wert gone</l>
               <l>My work would all be left undone;</l>
               <l>But that thou It ſlinck away thou Varlet,</l>
               <l>And leave me like forſaken Harlot?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quin etiam hyber no moliris ſydere claſſem,</l>
                        <l>Et mediis properas Aquilonibus ire per altum:</l>
                        <l>Crudelis—,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> In winter too, o're bluſtring Seas,</l>
               <l>When it 'twixt two a bed doth freeze?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Quid ſi non arva alicna, domoſque</l>
                        <l>Ignotas peteres?———</l>
                        <l>Mene ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gis?——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> What though thou hadſt as thou haſt none</l>
               <l>A Houſe to go to, of thine own,</l>
               <l>Could'ſt find yet in thy heart to 'reave me</l>
               <l>Of thy dear Company, and leave me?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———Per egohas lachrymas, dextramque tuam te,</l>
                        <l>Per Connu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ia noſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a, per incaeptos hymenaeos.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> By this laſt Rhume thou ſeeſt that wets</l>
               <l>My cheeks, and by thy hand that ſweats,</l>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:65925:36"/>
               <l>I'me Brief, by the whole matters Carriage</l>
               <l>And by the Earneſt of our Marriage:</l>
               <l>And by thoſe ſweet delights we ſtole,</l>
               <l>When the rayne drave thee into th' hole;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Si be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e quid te merui, fuit aut tibi quicquam</l>
                        <l>Dulce meum, miſerere domus labentis—</l>
                        <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> ſi quis adhuc precibus locus—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I fought there pleaſ'd thee, or ſince any</l>
               <l>Other delights, as we have had many,</l>
               <l>I do beſeech thee <hi>Trojan</hi> fine,</l>
               <l>Not to undo both me, and mine.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Te propter <hi>Lybicae</hi> gentes, Nomadumque Tyranni</l>
                        <l>Odere infenſi <hi>Tyrii;</hi> te propter eundem</l>
                        <l>Extinctus pudo,——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> For thy ſweet ſake the knaviſh <hi>Lydians,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Tyrians,</hi> and the vile <hi>Namidians,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In midſt of which is my abode,</l>
               <l>Hate me, as one would hate a Toad.</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:65925:37"/>
               <l>For thee I firſt forewent all ſhame,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Et quâ ſolâ ſidera adibam,</l>
                        <l>Fama P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And that I liv'd by my good name,</l>
               <l>And wilt thou having ſpent thy ardour,</l>
               <l>And eat me out of houſe and harbour,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">———Cui me moribundam deſeris hoſpes.</note> So baſely to my foes betray me,</l>
               <l>And neither ſtay with me, nor pay me?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quid moror? an mea Pygm lion dum maenia ſrater</l>
                        <l>Deſt ua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>? aut captam ducat Getulus Iarbas?</l>
                        <l>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ltem ſiqua mihi de te ſuſe pta ſuiſſet</l>
                        <l>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e fugam ſoboles, ſiquis mihi parvulus aula</l>
                        <l>Luderet Aeneas———</l>
                        <l>Non equidem omnino capta, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut deſerta viderer.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> No ſooner ſhall thy back be turn'd</l>
               <l>But all my building will be burn'd;</l>
               <l>That Rogue <hi>Pygmalion</hi> will ha' me,</l>
               <l>Or elſe <hi>Iarbas</hi> here will ta' me,</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:65925:37"/>
               <l>If (as we oft have ventur'd it,)</l>
               <l>I had but a big belly yet,</l>
               <l>A little <hi>Trojan</hi> comming on,</l>
               <l>To play withal, when thou art gone,</l>
               <l>Then let the Rogues do what they durſt do,</l>
               <l>I ſhould have ſomething yet to truſt to.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> t'ane thus baſely tardy,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Ille immota tenebat</l>
                        <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ina, et obnixus curam ſub corde premebat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Turnd pale; and like a ſtickt-pig ſtar'd ye:</l>
               <l>He could not ſtand upright but lean,</l>
               <l>One might have fell'd him with a bean;</l>
               <l>Nay he was ſtruck ſo at her ſpeeches,</l>
               <l>Some ſay he did defile his breeches,</l>
               <l>His bowels did ſo yearne upon her;</l>
               <l>But being that may wound his honor,</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:65925:38"/>
               <l>I'le not affirme it; but proceed,</l>
               <l>To tell you what he ſaid, and did;</l>
               <l>Much was he mov'd at <hi>Dido's</hi> words</l>
               <l>Which ſtab'd him through and through like ſwords:</l>
               <l>Much griev'd to ſee her weep, and ſob ſo,</l>
               <l>To throw about her ſnot, and throb ſo:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Merc'ryes</hi> Meſſage more prevailing</l>
               <l>Then her collouging or her rayling,</l>
               <l>After a many fine good-morrows,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tandem pauca refert, Ego te, quae plurima ſando</l>
                        <l>Enumerare vales, nunquam Regina negab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Promeritam.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> He thus began to falve her ſorrows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Should I (quoth he) O Queen deny,</l>
               <l>That thou'rt the flower of courteſie;</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:65925:38"/>
               <l>Or any ſlanders vile contrive,</l>
               <l>I were the baſeſt knave alive.</l>
               <l>I muſt confeſſe that thou O Queene,</l>
               <l>To mee, and to us all haſt beene</l>
               <l>More like a Mother, than a friend,</l>
               <l>So much Ile ſay, and there's an end;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Nec me meminiſſe pigebit <hi>Elizae,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m memor ipſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i, dum ſpiritus hos reget artus.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And if I ever do forget ye,</l>
               <l>Or fail to drink a Health to <hi>Betty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let me be hang'd as high, or higher</l>
               <l>Then topp of <hi>Cartbage</hi> ſteeple ſpire:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Pro re p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uca loqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r——:</note> Few words are beſt; if youl be civil,</l>
               <l>I'le tell the truth, and ſhame the Devil.<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Nec ego hanc abſcondere furto</l>
                        <l>Speravi (ne finge) ſugam.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:65925:39"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———Nec ego hanc abſcondere furto</l>
                        <l>Speravi (ne finge) ſugam——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I nere had thought, much leſſe deſire</l>
               <l>Baſely to build a ſconce at <hi>Tyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſteal away from thee my honey.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Nec conjugis unquam</l>
                        <l>Praetendi taeda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut haec in ſaedera veni.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But for the thing call'd Matrimony,</l>
               <l>Although I did the thing you wott,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> be my Judge I mean it not.</l>
               <l>Indeed I took it for a kindneſſe,</l>
               <l>To be familiar with your Highneſſe.</l>
               <l>But if I ever thought of other,</l>
               <l>Than one good turn requires another;</l>
               <l>Or on ſuch terms e're gave my fiſt,</l>
               <l>I'me th' arrantſt Rogue that ever piſt.</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:65925:39"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Me ſi fata meis paterentur ducere vitam</l>
                        <l>Anſpiciis, et ſponte mea componere curas.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I muſt confeſs that if it lay,</l>
               <l>In my own power, as one may ſay,</l>
               <l>That I had ſome good bargain made</l>
               <l>And bound my ſon here to a Trade,</l>
               <l>Plac'd all my followers, and therefore</l>
               <l>Had no one but my ſelf to care for,</l>
               <l>I would as willing match with you,</l>
               <l>As any woman that I know:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sed nunc <hi>Italiam</hi> magnam Gryneus <hi>Apollo,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Italiam Lyciae</hi> juſſere capeſſere ſortes,</l>
                        <l>Hic amor, haec p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tria eſt.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But as things ſtand, I needs muſt follow</l>
               <l>The councell of my friend <hi>Apollo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſends me word I muſt convey me</l>
               <l>To <hi>Lucia</hi> with all ſpeed that may be,</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:65925:40"/>
               <l>Where by a dainty rivers ſide,</l>
               <l>A farme lyes ready cut and dryd,</l>
               <l>Will hold both me, and all my meany,</l>
               <l>And cheap as fourty eggs a penny,</l>
               <l>There then in downright truth doe I</l>
               <l>Intend to live and occupy;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Si te <hi>Carthaginis</hi> arces</l>
                        <l>Phaeniſſam, <hi>Lybicaeque</hi> aſpectus detinet urbis,</l>
                        <l>Quae tandem Auſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ia Teucros co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſidere terra</l>
                        <l>Invidia eſt? et nos fas extera quaerere Regns.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And if ſo be that you who are ſage,</l>
               <l>Delight ſo in your Town of <hi>Carthage:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why ſhould it be in us ſo great ſin,</l>
               <l>Who have no Houſe to thruſt our heads in</l>
               <l>To travel to a forreign Nation,</l>
               <l>For ſome convenient habitation?</l>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:65925:40"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Me patris Anchiſae, quoties humentibus umbris</l>
                        <l>Nox operit terras, quoties aſtra ignea ſurgunt,</l>
                        <l>Admonet in ſomnis, et turbida terret Imago;</l>
                        <l>Me puer Aſcanius——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I can no ſooner go anights</l>
               <l>To Bed (<hi>Jove</hi> bleſs us all from ſprites)</l>
               <l>But that ere I can frame to ſnore,</l>
               <l>My Fathers Ghoſt comes through the dore</l>
               <l>Though ſhut as ſure as hands can make it,</l>
               <l>And leads me ſuch a fearful racket;</l>
               <l>I ſtew all night in my own greaſe,</l>
               <l>So that your mayds may, if they pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Wring from the ſhirt wherein I wallow,</l>
               <l>Each morning tyde, as much good tallow</l>
               <l>As well would liquor all their ſandals,</l>
               <l>And make beſide ſix pound of candles.</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:65925:41"/>
               <l>And all this is to have me gone,</l>
               <l>And not ſtay heret' undoe my ſon;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nunc etiam interpres divum <hi>Jove</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſus ab ipſo</l>
                        <l>———Celeres mandata per aur as</l>
                        <l>Detulit.———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Beſides, not paſt an hour ago,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> ſent his Lackquay to me too;</l>
               <l>I ſaw him fly, I'le<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Teſtor u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rumque caput.——</l>
                        <l>———Ipſe Deum manifeſto in lumine vidi</l>
                        <l>Intraniem muros, vocemque his auribus hauſi.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> take my oath,</l>
               <l>(And man has but his faith and troth)</l>
               <l>As plainly ore your dairy top,</l>
               <l>As ere I ſaw him on the rope:</l>
               <l>And heard him ſpeak as plain but ene now,</l>
               <l>As I hear you, or you hear me now.</l>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:65925:41"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſine meque tuis incendere teque querelis;</l>
                        <l>Italiam non ſponte ſequor.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Then let me be ſo much beholding,</l>
               <l>Unto your Grace to leave your ſcolding;</l>
               <l>For I this voyage undertake,</l>
               <l>Even like a Bear that's drawn to th' ſtake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Talia dicentem jamdudum averſa tuetur,</l>
                        <l>Huc illuc, volvens oculos, totumque pererrat</l>
                        <l>Lunimibus tacitis, &amp; ſic accenſa profatur.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> This ſaid, the Queen in wrathful wiſe,</l>
               <l>Rowling about her goggle eyes,</l>
               <l>As ſhe would throw'um in his face,</l>
               <l>Unto her fury thus gave place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Stinkard (quoth ſhe) now thy falſe heart</l>
               <l>Show's what a cheating knave thou art:</l>
               <l>The Symptomes of a Rogue thou haſt all,</l>
               <l>Thou a true <hi>Trojan,</hi> thou a Raſcall!</l>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:65925:42"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nec te diva parens, generis nec Daedanus author</l>
                        <l>Perfide: ſed duris genuit te cautibus horrens</l>
                        <l>Caucaſus, Hyrcanaeque admorunt ubera Tigres.</l>
                        <l>Nam quid diſſimulo?——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> No man or woman of good faſhion,</l>
               <l>Ere coupled for thy Procreation;</l>
               <l>But whelpt thou wert of Tinkers bitch,</l>
               <l>Under ſome hedge, or in ſome ditch:</l>
               <l>Nay, I'le not balke you Sir; nor care,</l>
               <l>For all you look ſo big and ſtare:</l>
               <l>Let thy foul hide with malice burſt,</l>
               <l>I do defie thee, do thy worſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Num fletu ingenuit noſtro? num lumina fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>it?</l>
                        <l>Num lac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ymas victus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dit? aut miſeratus amantem eſt?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Inſtead of ſighing in this caſe,</l>
               <l>Full ſoure thou belcheſt in my face;</l>
               <l>And thou ſo ſtubborn art and cankerd,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhed'ſt no tears, but tears o'th' Tankerd.</l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:65925:42"/>
               <l>Had'ſt thou but counterfeited paſſion,</l>
               <l>To ſignifie commiſeration,</l>
               <l>Or offer'd but a ſour face, it</l>
               <l>Had been a ſign of ſome ſmall grace yet;</l>
               <l>But like a logger-headed Lubber,</l>
               <l>Thou grinning ſtand'ſt, and ſeeſt me blubber</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Jam jam nec maxima <hi>Juno,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nec <hi>Saturnius</hi> haec oculis pater aſpicit aequis.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And <hi>Jove</hi> nor <hi>Juno,</hi> for ought I ſee,</l>
               <l>Will neither of 'um both chaſtiſe thee.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nuſquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uta fides! ejectum littore egentem</l>
                        <l>Excepi,———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> There's no truth in this age we live in</l>
               <l>A wandring beggar hither driven;</l>
               <l>Who had when weak as he could crawl,</l>
               <l>No croſs to bleſs himſelf withal;</l>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:65925:43"/>
               <l>I have receiv'd to bed and board,</l>
               <l>Feaſted, and clad him like a Lord,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———Et regn demens in parte locavi:</l>
                        <l>——Nunc augur <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And (like a ſimple haire-brain'd jade)</l>
               <l>This youth Haile-fellow with me made:</l>
               <l>And now forſooth he cannot ſtay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> bids him run away.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Amiſſam claſſem, ſocios a monte reduxi.</note> Nay though I have in friendly wiſe</l>
               <l>Cur'd his mens ſcabs and kill'd their lice:</l>
               <l>Yet having now fall'n to his lot,</l>
               <l>A good rich Farm lies piping hot:</l>
               <l>Should he ſtay here, it would undo him,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Jove</hi> has ſent his footman to him;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nunc <hi>Lyciae</hi> ſortes, nunc &amp; <hi>Jove</hi> miſſus ab ipſo</l>
                        <l>Interpres divûm fert horrida juſſ a per auras;</l>
                        <l>Scilicet is ſuperis labor eſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a cura quietos</l>
                        <l>Sollicitat———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:65925:43"/>
               <l>As if the Deities were ſo</l>
               <l>Concern'd, they'd nothing elſe to do,</l>
               <l>But ſend their Lacquais, and their Pages</l>
               <l>To him on how-dees and meſſages.</l>
               <l>But I'le waſte on thee no more breath,</l>
               <l>For whom the wind that fumes beneath,</l>
               <l>Is far too ſweet: Avant thou ſlave!</l>
               <l>Thou lying Cony-catching Knave,</l>
               <l>Be moving, do as thou haſt told me!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>I ſequere <hi>Italiam</hi> ventis,—</l>
                        <l>——Neque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e teneo—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> No body here intends to hold thee!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Pete regna per undas.</l>
                        <l>Spero equidem mediis———</l>
                        <l>Supplicia hauſurum ſcopulis——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Go! ſeek thy Farm, I hope 'twill be</l>
               <l>I'th' very bottom of the Sea:</l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:65925:44"/>
               <l>But ſhould'ſt thou ſcape, and not in Dike-ly,</l>
               <l>Drown'd like a puppy as 'tis likely,</l>
               <l>Since in the Proverb old 'tis found,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe born to hang will nere be drown'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet ſhould'ſt thou not be much the nigher,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Sequar atris ignibus abſens:</l>
                        <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t cum frigida mors anima reduxerit artus,</l>
                        <l>Ommibus umbra locis adero.—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I'le haunt thee like a going fire,</l>
               <l>As ſoon as I can turn t'a Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>Which will be in a week at moſt:</l>
               <l>Then in the mid-night ſleep I'le wake thee,</l>
               <l>And ride thee worſe than any Haokney.</l>
               <l>I'le terrifie thee day and night;</l>
               <l>Nay if thou do'ſt but go to—</l>
               <l>There will I ſtand with flaming taper,</l>
               <l>To Fizze thy tail inſtead of paper.</l>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:65925:44"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">——Dabis improbe paenas.</note> I'le make thee rue the time that ere</l>
               <l>Thou cam'ſt to play thy knaves tricks here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>His medium dictis ſermonem abrumpit &amp; auras</l>
                        <l>Aegra fugit,——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> In middle of this wrathful ſpeech</l>
               <l>Down drops Queen <hi>Dido</hi> on her breech:</l>
               <l>Her mouth was ſtopt, and on the ground</l>
               <l>She ſilent lay in doleful ſwound:</l>
               <l>Shut were her eyes; nor had ſhe hearing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>For what <hi>Aeneas</hi> was<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Linquens multa metu cunctantem, &amp; multa parantem</l>
                        <l>Dicere———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Preparing,</l>
               <l>Upon this pitiful occaſion,</l>
               <l>To ſay in's own juſtification.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In haſte the <hi>Trojans</hi> all advance</l>
               <l>To 'wake her Grace out of her trance;</l>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:65925:45"/>
               <l>They try'd to raiſe her in ſuch ſort,</l>
               <l>As when men cry, <hi>Le corps eſt mort:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But here the Charm would not prevail,</l>
               <l>They could not raiſe her from her tail:</l>
               <l>For though full light, when her own woman</l>
               <l>Yet in this heavy dump was no man</l>
               <l>Could raiſe her up, though nere ſo mighty,</l>
               <l>Sorrow had made her bum ſo weighty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Suſcipiunt famulae, collapſaque membra</l>
                        <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rmore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> referunt thalamo, ſtratiſque reponunt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> At laſt a crew of ſtrapping jades,</l>
               <l>That were, or ſhould have been her Maids,</l>
               <l>Gath'ring her up away convey'd her,</l>
               <l>And having in her own bed laid her,</l>
               <l>With rugs they boulſter'd her about,</l>
               <l>To try if ſhe could ſweat it out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:65925:45"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>At pius <hi>Aeneas,</hi> quanquam lenire dolentem</l>
                        <l>Solando cupit, &amp; dictis avertere curas,</l>
                        <l>Multa gemens, magnoque animum labeſactus amore:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> though 'twas his deſire,</l>
               <l>Something t' have ſaid might pacifie her,</l>
               <l>And though his heart did bleed within him,</l>
               <l>To think of what had paſt between 'um,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſſa tamen divûm exequitur</hi>——</note> Yet becauſe <hi>Jove</hi> ſo loud did threaten,</l>
               <l>He ſooner durſt his nails have eaten,</l>
               <l>Having ſo terribly been chidden,</l>
               <l>Than not t' have done as he was bidden.</l>
               <l>Therefore in haſte his hoſteſs beck'ning,</l>
               <l>To come, and bring 'um in a reck'ning:</l>
               <l>Straight to the wharfe repayres the hot-ſhot,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Claſſemque reviſit</l>
                        <l>Tum vero T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ri incumbunt &amp; littore celſas</l>
                        <l>Deducunt to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o naves:———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Without once calling for his ſhot-pot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:65925:46"/>
               <l>The <hi>Tojans</hi> now by his commiſſion,</l>
               <l>Lanch all their Boats with expedition;</l>
               <l>You now upon the Ocean might ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Natat uncta carima:</l>
                        <l>Frondenteſque feruat remos, &amp; robora ſilvis</l>
                        <l>Infabricata.———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> The new greas'd wherries ſwim moſt lightly,</l>
               <l>They had new made 'um fine long poles,</l>
               <l>New pitcht their oars, and made new thoules;</l>
               <l>Though many things were left undone,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">——Fugae ſtudio.</note> They were ſo eager to be gone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Migrantes cernas, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otaque ex urbe ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tes.</note> Then might you ſee'um make their Sallies</l>
               <l>From <hi>Carthage</hi> Town, through lanes and allies,</l>
               <l>Stealing away with lewd intentions,</l>
               <l>To cheat the <hi>Tyrians</hi> of their penſions,</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:65925:46"/>
               <l>Fearing their Landlad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es would brabble,</l>
               <l>And dun 'um for their quarters table.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ac veluti ingentem formicae farris acervum</l>
                        <l>Cum populant hyemis memores, tectoque reponunt.</l>
                        <l>—It campis agmen, praedamque per herbas</l>
                        <l>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>vectant calle anguſto, pars grandia trudunt</l>
                        <l>Obnixae f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>umenta humeris, pars——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> As Hedg-hogs when they go to th' wood,</l>
               <l>To fetch a hoard of Winter food,</l>
               <l>Return well laden with their vittles,</l>
               <l>Fine yellow Crabs ſtuck round their prickles</l>
               <l>Even ſo the <hi>Trojans</hi> with our doubt,</l>
               <l>Were at this ſeaſon hung about</l>
               <l>With fardles, bundles, bags and wallets,</l>
               <l>To cloath their backs, and feed their pallats.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quis tibi tunc <hi>Dido</hi> cernenti talia ſeaſus?</l>
                        <l>——Cum littora fervere late</l>
                        <l>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oſpiceres arce ex ſumma, totumque videres</l>
                        <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſceri ante oculos tautis clamoribus aequor.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But what thought <hi>Dido</hi> in this caſe,</l>
               <l>When thus ſhe ſaw them ſlink their wayes,</l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:65925:47"/>
               <l>From Garret-window ſaw 'um row,</l>
               <l>And heard 'um crying <hi>Eaſt-ward</hi> Hoe!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Improbe AMOR, quid non mortalia pectora cogis?</hi>
                  </note> To ſee how love makes folks do things,</l>
               <l>Againſt the hair, againſt the ſhins!</l>
               <l>For ſhe though full of indignation,</l>
               <l>To be forſaken in this faſhion;</l>
               <l>And had ſhe known but how to get him,</l>
               <l>Could doubtleſs without ſalt have eat him:</l>
               <l>Yet n'ertheleſs, love over-ruling,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ire iterum in lacrymas, iterum tentare precaudo</l>
                        <l>Cogitur———</l>
                        <l>Nequid inexpertum fruſtra moritura relinquat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> She fell again to her old puling;</l>
               <l>And once more meant to try if pitty</l>
               <l>Would not recal him to the City.</l>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:65925:47"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Anna,</hi> vides toto properari lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore circum:</note> Look thee (quoth ſhe) where he (my <hi>Nancy</hi>)</l>
               <l>Whoſe able parts I do much fancy,</l>
               <l>Has truſtt up all his tools together,</l>
               <l>To carry 'um the Lord knowes whither.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Vocat jam ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>baſus auras,</l>
                        <l>Puppibus &amp; laethi nautae impoſuere coronas.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Hark how his rabble gange do ſhout<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And ſhove a ſtern to haſten out;</l>
               <l>A rout of baſe unthankful peaſants!</l>
               <l>The Devil cut their yelping weazens:</l>
               <l>The bawling Raſcals egge him on,</l>
               <l>And make him madder to be gon.</l>
               <l>Had I once dreamt the <hi>Tearing</hi> Devil</l>
               <l>Could ever have been ſo uncivil,</l>
               <l>Thus like a jade to break his teather;</l>
               <l>I ſhould have kept my legs together:</l>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:65925:48"/>
               <l>Or have made bold t' have tide him faſter,</l>
               <l>To the due limits of his paſture:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Soror miſerae hoc tamen unum</l>
                        <l>Exequere <hi>Anna</hi> mihi; ſolam nam perfidus ille</l>
                        <l>Te c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lere, arcanos eliam tibi credere ſenſus.</l>
                        <l>Sola viri molles aditus, &amp; tempora noras.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But ſince he holds me at this diſtance,</l>
               <l>I beg thy ſiſterly aſſiſtance:</l>
               <l>Thou knoweſt the temper of the block-head,</l>
               <l>And to a hair canſt fit his pocket:</l>
               <l>Therefore (dear <hi>Nancy</hi>) I implore thee,</l>
               <l>If ere thou'lt do any thing for mee,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>I ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or atque hoſtem ſupplex affare ſuperbum.</hi>
                  </note> Run to the wharf with might and main,</l>
               <l>And try to bring him back again:</l>
               <l>I promiſe thee, and if I break</l>
               <l>My word; pray <hi>Jove</hi> I break my neck.</l>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:65925:48"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Extremam hanc oro veniam (miſerere Sororis)</l>
                        <l>Quam mihi cum dederis, cumulatam morte relinquam.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> If thou canſt bring him to my bow,</l>
               <l>I'le give thee for thy pains a Cow.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non ego cum <hi>Danais Trojanam</hi> exſcindere gentem</l>
                        <l>Aulide juravi, claſſemve ad <hi>Pergama</hi> miſi:</l>
                        <l>Nec patris <hi>Anchiſae</hi> cineres, maneſve revelli.</l>
                        <l>Cur mea dicta negat duras demittere in aures?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Tell him I ere had more diſcretion,</l>
               <l>Then to joyn iſſues with the <hi>Graecian:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I neither did meddle nor make,</l>
               <l>But <hi>as they brew'd, ſo let them bake:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor did I ere make skittle-pin-bones,</l>
               <l>Or bobbins of <hi>Anchiſes</hi> ſhin-bones:</l>
               <l>Why ſhould he then without all ſence,</l>
               <l>Thus uſe me like a Kitchin-wench?</l>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:65925:49"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">—Extremum hoc miſerae det munus amanti.</note> I would but beg one kindneſs from him:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non jam conjugium antiquum, quod prodidit, oro;</l>
                        <l>Tempus inane peto, requiem, ſpaciumque—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I will no more claim promiſe on him:</l>
               <l>But only that he'l tarry here,</l>
               <l>Half or a quarter of a year;</l>
               <l>Whereby I may, before he go,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Dum mea me victam doceat fortuna dolere.</note> Wean my ſelf from a Bed fellow:</l>
               <l>Or (if my conſtitution can,</l>
               <l>Not well ſubſiſt without a man)</l>
               <l>Until I can my ſelf ſupply,</l>
               <l>With one to do my drudgery.</l>
               <l>I'le ask no further obligation,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Nec pulchro ut <hi>Latio</hi> careat reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umque reliaquat.</note> But let him to his Navigation;</l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:65925:49"/>
               <l>He may to <hi>Latium</hi> then addreſs,</l>
               <l>And ſwim, or ſink, all's one to <hi>Beſs.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Talibus orabat, taleſque miſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rima fletus</l>
                        <l>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tque refertque ſoror——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Scarce had the woful <hi>Dido</hi> done,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Nan</hi> prepar'd her to be gone,</l>
               <l>She tacks her coats about her hanches,</l>
               <l>And to the waters ſide advances:</l>
               <l>She tript ſo neatly to the Pyre,</l>
               <l>It would have done one good to ſee her:</l>
               <l>One would have thought ſhe'd gone in haſt,</l>
               <l>Midwife to fetch, ſhe went ſo faſt.</l>
               <l>At laſt ſhe came unto the place</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Dido's</hi> dear <hi>Aeneas</hi> was;</l>
               <l>She found him ſit amongſt his mates,</l>
               <l>The reſt o'th' <hi>Trojan</hi> runnagates,</l>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:65925:50"/>
               <l>Pufft like a foot-ball with vain glory,</l>
               <l>Roaring and drinking tory lory;</l>
               <l>Like one that knew a pot i'th' pate,</l>
               <l>Would be a mile or two i'th' gate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Trojan</hi> had no ſooner ſpide her,</l>
               <l>But though he could not well abide her,</l>
               <l>Yet cauſe he would part fairly with her,</l>
               <l>He askt what wind had blown her thither.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She putting finger in the eye,</l>
               <l>(As Women when they liſt can cry)</l>
               <l>Told him in what a ſad condition,</l>
               <l>Her ſiſter was: her laſt petition,</l>
               <l>And pray'd him as he was a true man,</l>
               <l>Not to undoe a proper Woman.</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:65925:50"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Sed nullis ille movetur</l>
                        <l>Fletibus, aut voces ullas tractabilis audit.</l>
                        <l>——Lachryinae volvuntur inanes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But ſhe might een have ſav'd her juice,</l>
               <l>And kept her tears for better uſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Fata obſtant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—</note> His reſolution ſtill oppoſes,</l>
               <l>He would go ſpite of all their noſes;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ac veluti annoſam valido cum robore quercum</l>
                        <l>Alpini Boreae nunc hinc nunc flatibus illinc</l>
                        <l>Erue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e inter ſe certant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>——</l>
                        <l>Ipſa lae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>et ſcopulis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>——</l>
                        <l>Haud ſecus aſſiduts hinc, alque hinc vocibus heros</l>
                        <l>Tunditur———</l>
                        <l>Mens immota manet——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And like to hemp, which, as I take it,</l>
               <l>The more you twiſt, you ſtronger make it:</l>
               <l>Even ſo, the more ſhe try'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wind him,</l>
               <l>She ſtill more obſtinate did find him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Tum vero infelix fatis exterrita <hi>Dido.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>Dido</hi> madder grew and madder,</l>
               <l>No friend ſhe had could now perſwade her;</l>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:65925:51"/>
               <l>She ſtamp'd, and ſtar'd, as ſhe were wood,</l>
               <l>And in her melancholy mood,</l>
               <l>Calling to minde in wofull wiſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> and his treacheries,</l>
               <l>How often he had ſtab'd her Honor,</l>
               <l>That men would now make Ballads on her;</l>
               <l>She was reſolv'd without delay,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tem orat: taedet coeli convexa tueri,</l>
                        <l>Quo magis inceptum perag at, lucemque relinquat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Fairly to make her ſelf away,</l>
               <l>And meant to put her reſolution</l>
               <l>Into moſt tragick execution.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She had alaſs! too juſt incitement</l>
               <l>Thus to prefer her own Indictment;</l>
               <l>And reaſon good, by all relation,</l>
               <l>Thus to proceed to condemnation:</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:65925:51"/>
               <l>For ſuch portents, and dite preſages,</l>
               <l>As ſtill have been diſaſters pages,</l>
               <l>Foretold her overthrow ſo plainly,</l>
               <l>She ſaw t' oppoſe it would in vain be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Vidit, thuri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>remis cum dona imponeret dris,</l>
                        <l>Horrendum dictu, latices nigreſcere ſacros,</l>
                        <l>Fuſaque in obſcoenum ſe vertere vina cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rem.</l>
                        <l>Hoc viſum nulli, non ipſi effata ſorori.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> She call'd to waſh, and do you think,</l>
               <l>The water turn'd as black as Ink;</l>
               <l>And that by chance being cherning day,</l>
               <l>Her cream moſt ſtrangely turned to whay!</l>
               <l>This <hi>Dido</hi> ſaw, but would by no means</l>
               <l>Tell her own Siſter of the omens.</l>
               <l>But that which gave the moſt perſwaſion,</l>
               <l>Unto her fell determination,</l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:65925:52"/>
               <l>Was this: (t) ſhe kept <hi>Sichaeus</hi> bones</l>
               <l>In a great Coffer made o'th' nonce,</l>
               <l>As ſundry others have done the-like,</l>
               <l>By way of Superſtitious Relicke,</l>
               <l>In a dark Cellar under ground,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hinc exaudiri voces, &amp; verba vocantis</l>
                        <l>Viſa viri; nox cum terras obſcura teneret.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> From whence each night a diſmal ſound,</l>
               <l>Pierc't <hi>Didos</hi> tender ear, and wiſht her,</l>
               <l>Nay like a husband admoniſht her,</l>
               <l>To fit her for her latter end,</l>
               <l>For why he told her, as a friend,</l>
               <l>That in a very ſhort ſpace, ſhe</l>
               <l>Should of this world, no woman be.</l>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:65925:52"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Solaque culminibus ferali carmine bubo</l>
                        <l>Saepe queri———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> The Scrich-Owles too, were her moleſters,</l>
               <l>Who ſtill were chanting out their veſpers:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Multaque praeterea vatum praedicta priorum</l>
                        <l>Terribili monitu horrificant—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Beſides ſhe had her Fortune told her</l>
               <l>When 'bout ſome dozen or ſo, no older,</l>
               <l>That ſhe ſhould but one Husband have,</l>
               <l>And after that a ſcurvy Knave,</l>
               <l>Should ſteal her honour like a thief,</l>
               <l>And make her hang her ſelf for grief:</l>
               <l>Theſe ſad portents falling ſo thick,</l>
               <l>And pat on one anothers neck,</l>
               <l>Put the poor Queen beſide her ſenſes,</l>
               <l>As a juſt plague for her offences.</l>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:65925:53"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Agit ipſc furentem</l>
                        <l>In ſomnis ferus <hi>Aeneas,</hi> ſemperque relinqui</l>
                        <l>Sola ſibi, ſemper longam incomitata videtur</l>
                        <l>Ire viam——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> She dreams <hi>Aeneas</hi> now is going,</l>
               <l>Like a falſe friend to her undoing,</l>
               <l>And that ſhe muſt when <hi>Trojan</hi> goes,</l>
               <l>For ever loſe her play fellowes.</l>
               <l>Which to a woman's cauſe ſufficient,</l>
               <l>Let her be ne're ſo well condition'd,</l>
               <l>To raiſe her to extravagancies,</l>
               <l>When ſhe muſt part with what ſhe fancies.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Eum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nidum veluti demens videt agmina Pentheus,</l>
                        <l>Aut <hi>Agamemnonius</hi> ſcenis agitatus Oreſtes,</l>
                        <l>Illa ita concepit furiis——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Even as a bitches fury up is,</l>
               <l>When people come to ſteal her puppies:</l>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65925:53"/>
               <l>So far'd the wrathful Queen that day</l>
               <l>When <hi>Bilbo</hi> muſt be tane away:</l>
               <l>She was ſo much concern'd about him,</l>
               <l>She could not, would not live without him:</l>
               <l>But in her deſperate reſolutions,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Decrevi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>que mori, tempus ſecum ipſa modumque</l>
                        <l>Exigit, &amp; moeſtam dictis aggreſſa ſororem,</l>
                        <l>Conſilium vultu tegit, ac ſpem fronte ſernat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> would hang her ſelf to try concluſions.</l>
               <l>The time and manner ſhe projected,</l>
               <l>And that ſhe might not be ſuſpected,</l>
               <l>She ſmug'd her viſage up with ſmiles,</l>
               <l>And thus her Siſter <hi>Nan</hi> beguils.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Inveni germana viam (gratare ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ori)</l>
                        <l>Qua mihi reddat eum,——</l>
                        <l>——Vel co me ſolvat am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ntem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nancy</hi> (quoth ſhe) I've found at laſt</l>
               <l>A way, for all <hi>Aeneas</hi> haſt;</l>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:65925:54"/>
               <l>If thou in the exploit wilt joyn,</l>
               <l>Shall pay him back in his own coin,</l>
               <l>And bring him back by our contriving,</l>
               <l>Since he's ſo goodly, Dead, or living.</l>
               <l>Seeing the Rogue my love diſgraces,</l>
               <l>I'le ſpoil his ſport in other places.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Oceani finem juxta, ſolemque cadentem,</l>
                        <l>Ultimus <hi>Aethiopum</hi> locus eſt; ubi maximus <hi>Atlas</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m humero torquet,——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> A mile from hence, or ſuch a ſpace,</l>
               <l>Down in a bottom lies a place,</l>
               <l>Farr out of all high-wayes and roads,</l>
               <l>Where nothing breeds, but Frogs and Toads,</l>
               <l>Snakes, adders, and ſuch wicked vermin,</l>
               <l>That (can they catch 'um) will not ſpare men:</l>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:65925:54"/>
               <l>There in a Cave lies an old<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hinc mihi <hi>Maſly lae</hi> gentis monſtrata ſacerdos,</l>
                        <l>Heſperidum templi cuſtos; epulaſque draconi</l>
                        <l>Quae dabat,————</l>
                        <l>Spargens humida m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lla, ſoporiferumque papaver.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> wretch,</l>
               <l>An ugly rotten toothleſs witch,</l>
               <l>So old that one would think ſhe were,</l>
               <l>The eldeſt Devils Grand-mother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>c ſe carminibus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>omitti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſolvere mentes</l>
                        <l>Quas velit; aſt aliis duras immittere curas:</l>
                        <l>Siſtere aquam fluviis, &amp; vertere ſidera retro;</l>
                        <l>Nocturnoſque ciet manes; mugire videbis</l>
                        <l>Sub pedibus terram, &amp; deſcendere montibus ornos.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Now this old Beldame can do wonders,</l>
               <l>If ſhe but ſay the word it Thunders,</l>
               <l>Lightens, or Rains, or Hails, or Snows,</l>
               <l>Or any weather you'l ſuppoſe.</l>
               <l>She'l make a Cowle-ſtaffe, by her ſpelling,</l>
               <l>Amble like any double Gelding;</l>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:65925:55"/>
               <l>And in the dead of night the baſe-hag</l>
               <l>Can of a cudgel make a race-Nag:</l>
               <l>A Walnut ſhe to Sea can rig out,</l>
               <l>And of an Egg-ſhell make a Friggot;</l>
               <l>Nay in a thimble ſtemme the flood,</l>
               <l>Provide the thimble be of wood.</l>
               <l>She can, where ſhe does owe a ſpite,</l>
               <l>Spoil any Bride-groom's wedding-night,</l>
               <l>And the Brides longing diſappoint,</l>
               <l>By vertue of a Cod-piece-point.</l>
               <l>She can make people love or hate,</l>
               <l>Ev'n whom ſhe pleaſe, and at what rate;</l>
               <l>And by her Magick, and her Spells,</l>
               <l>Make folks, or hang, or drown themſelves.</l>
               <l>In ſhort, there's nothing that has ill in't,</l>
               <l>But ſhe has admirable skill in't;</l>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:65925:55"/>
               <l>And does her miſchiefs too as quick,</l>
               <l>As any Jugler does a trick.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Teſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> chara, deos, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e germana, tuumque</l>
                        <l>Dulce ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut, magicas invitam accingier artes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I take the Gods to witneſs Siſter,</l>
               <l>I'me led into this courſe ſiniſter,</l>
               <l>Out of no end men wicked call;</l>
               <l>But only for revenge, that's all.</l>
               <l>And ſince I am ſo baſely croſt,</l>
               <l>I'le have this Hag, or it ſhall coſt</l>
               <l>More then I'le ſpeak of; ſhe perchance</l>
               <l>May lead my <hi>Trojan</hi> ſuch a dance,</l>
               <l>Shall make him glad as faſt as may be,</l>
               <l>To come again, and cry <hi>peccavi;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or make him hang himſelf at leaſt,</l>
               <l>For an example to the reſt</l>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:65925:56"/>
               <l>O'th' tribe of falſe diſſembling Yeomen,</l>
               <l>That take a pride to ruin Women:</l>
               <l>And by good luck ſhe's now hard by here,</l>
               <l>Come not an hour ago to <hi>Tyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sent for it ſeems about no ill deed,</l>
               <l>To bleſs a Sow that lies in Child-bed,</l>
               <l>And I'le go fetch her by her favour</l>
               <l>With a <hi>Sub-poena,</hi> but I'le have her.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tu ſecreta pyram tecto interiore ſub au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>as</l>
                        <l>Erige:————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> In the mean time; go thou and tie</l>
               <l>Faſt to the great beam, where I lie,</l>
               <l>The beſt new halter thou canſt chooſe,</l>
               <l>And make a dainty running nooſe;</l>
               <l>Like that fell to the fellow's ſhare,</l>
               <l>That made a Woman of a Mare.</l>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:65925:56"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Et arma viri, thalamo quae fixa reliquit</l>
                        <l>Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ius, exuviaſque omnes, lectumque jugalem,</l>
                        <l>Quo perii, ſuperimponas:——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Then take me out <hi>Aeneas</hi> rayment,</l>
               <l>All I have left in part of payment:</l>
               <l>His greaſie doublet, and his trowſes,</l>
               <l>Where many a wandring <hi>Trojan</hi> louſe is:</l>
               <l>The treaſure he has left behind him.</l>
               <l>In the great ſtanding Preſs, you'l find 'um:</l>
               <l>Stuffe me 'um up with ſtraw or litter,</l>
               <l>The worſe the ſtuffing is, the fitter:</l>
               <l>And ramme the tatters with a vengeance,</l>
               <l>As people uſe to ramme their Engines:</l>
               <l>Make haſte, and do as I have bid ye;</l>
               <l>I'le hang the Raſcal in Effigie:</l>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:65925:57"/>
               <l>So I'me advis'd to do, and ſo</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Abolere nefandi</l>
                        <l>Cuncta viri monumenta jubet monſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>que ſacerdos.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I mean to ſerve him, if I blow;</l>
               <l>Which, though I cannot wreak my teen, it</l>
               <l>Will ſtay the ſtomach of my Spleen yet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Haec effata ſilet; pallor ſimul occupat ora.</note> Thus having ſaid, the Queen chang'd colour,</l>
               <l>No Ghoſt cold e're look pittifuller.</l>
               <l>One would have thought by her dejection,</l>
               <l>And by her woful wan complexion,</l>
               <l>She had been going juſt o'th' ſuddain,</l>
               <l>To drop, and give the Crow a pudding.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non tamen <hi>Anna</hi> novis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aetexere funera ſacris</l>
                        <l>Germanam credit: nec tantos meute ſurores</l>
                        <l>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cipit, aut graviora timet.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nancy</hi> (although ſhe ſaw the Queen</l>
               <l>Ready to burſt her hoops for teen)</l>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:65925:57"/>
               <l>And well enough mark't how ſhe look't too,</l>
               <l>Yet by her fine pretence was rook't ſo,</l>
               <l>She did no further on't conſider,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Ergo juſta Parat.——</note> But went about what ſhe had bid her;</l>
               <l>Dreaming no more, than her laſt Even,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dido</hi> had been ſo lewdly given.</l>
               <l>Away therefore my laſs does trot,</l>
               <l>And preſently an halter got,</l>
               <l>Made of the beſt ſtrong hempen teere,</l>
               <l>And ere a Cat could lick her eare,</l>
               <l>Had tide it up with as much art,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Donne</hi> himſelf could do for's heart:</l>
               <l>The rope, and ſay't was got o'th' ſuddaine,</l>
               <l>Did prove ſo prime a ſpecial good one,</l>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:65925:58"/>
               <l>That with fair uſage it might come,</l>
               <l>To hang up <hi>Carthage</hi> all and ſome.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Trojans</hi> doublet ſhe had fill'd ſo,</l>
               <l>'Twas very ſtrange the buttons held ſo;</l>
               <l>And that the craming of his breeches</l>
               <l>Had not quite broken out the ſtitches:</l>
               <l>His very ſtockings, though they were</l>
               <l>About the feet out of repair;</l>
               <l>Yet ſhe made ſhift to ſtuff each ſtart-up,</l>
               <l>And tie 'um to the reſt on's wardrope:</l>
               <l>Having thus brac'd him like a Drumme,</l>
               <l>She laid him out in <hi>Dido</hi>'s room;</l>
               <l>(e) Diſplay'd upon a fair long board,</l>
               <l>Ready when <hi>Dido</hi> gave the word<note place="margin">(o)
<lg>
                        <l>——Exuvias, enſemque relictum,</l>
                        <l>Eſſigiemque toro locat,———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:65925:58"/>
               <l>To be advanc't into the halter,</l>
               <l>Without the benefit on's Pſalter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Scarce had ſhe thus diſpos'd her trinckums,</l>
               <l>When up the ſtaires behold the Queen comes,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Stant arae circum, &amp; crines effuſa facerdos.</note> Lading along th' old rotten Grammer,</l>
               <l>Into her Highneſs matted Chamber.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When ſhe was come, and ſaw the portly</l>
               <l>Trophy in that moſt noble ſort lye,</l>
               <l>As ſhe oft-times had ſeen the ſinner</l>
               <l>Lie gorg'd on benches after dinner:</l>
               <l>She fell again into a paſſion</l>
               <l>Caus'd by a ſweet commemoration</l>
               <l>Of paſt delights, ſeeing thoſe breeches,</l>
               <l>And humbly the old Gib beſeeches</l>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:65925:59"/>
               <l>To ſhew her utmoſt skill and cunning,</l>
               <l>To keep her <hi>Trojan</hi> dear from running.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The mumbling Witch bad her not fear,</l>
               <l>But reſt content, and of good chear,</l>
               <l>And ſhe ſhould ſee ſhe'd make him ſtay,</l>
               <l>Or foul her Art ſhould ſay her nay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ter centum tonat ore D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>os, Erebumquo, Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſque,</l>
                        <l>Tergeminamque Hecaten, tria virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nis ora <hi>Dianae.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> With that the Hag began her charm,</l>
               <l>You would have thought ſhee'd had a ſwarm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Of Waſps, or Hornets in her throat,</l>
               <l>There came ſo ſtrange a humming out:</l>
               <l>And as ſhe ſpoke, her hollow chaps</l>
               <l>Bound up in two thin ſhrivell'd flaps</l>
               <l>Of old abominable leather,</l>
               <l>Like bellows heav'd and clapt together.</l>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:65925:59"/>
               <l>Her little eyes being fiery red,</l>
               <l>Were ſunk ſo far into her head,</l>
               <l>They lookt, when moſt ſhe ſtar'd at full,</l>
               <l>Like farthing Candles in a Scull.</l>
               <l>Her noſe hung like an arch between</l>
               <l>Her wrinkled fore-head and her chin.</l>
               <l>A craggy paſſage, and uncouth,</l>
               <l>Over the dreadful gulf, her mouth,</l>
               <l>And Elf-locks hung ſo, on each ſhoulder,</l>
               <l>'Twould make one tremble to behold her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Witch a ribble-row rehearſes,</l>
               <l>Of ſcurvy names in ſcurvy verſes,</l>
               <l>Which by the manner of her mouthing,</l>
               <l>Was certainly <hi>Burleſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> or nothing.</l>
               <l>And in theſe rhythms as round ſhe limps,</l>
               <l>Calls her Familiars and her Imps,</l>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:65925:60"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Sparſerat, &amp; latices ſimulatos fontis Averni:</note> Sprinkling the Chamber in her motion</l>
               <l>With a tepid brackiſh lotion,</l>
               <l>For ought I know, of her own making,</l>
               <l>By her much ſtirring, and pains taking.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Queritur &amp; naſcentis equi de fronte revulſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Et matri praereptus amor.———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> A red-heart breaker next ſhe mow'd off,</l>
               <l>A wart that <hi>Dido</hi> was full proud of,</l>
               <l>And burnt it for a ſtrong purfume,</l>
               <l>And pow'rful ſpell to make him come.</l>
               <l>Then hand in hand to dance they fall,</l>
               <l>A grave and ſolemn Magick brawl,</l>
               <l>In ſuch hard figures none could tread um,</l>
               <l>But the old hobling hag that led um.</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Dido</hi> too alaſs! made one,</l>
               <l>Although her dancing dayes were done.</l>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:65925:60"/>
               <l>And though oppreſt with woe, and care, cut</l>
               <l>Capers, and Tricotee'd it<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Unum exuta pedem vinclis——</l>
                        <l>Teſtaturque Deos.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> barefoot;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Tum ſi quod non aequo ſoedere amant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</l>
                        <l>Cura num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a habet, juſtumque m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>o, que proca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Imploring all the Deities,</l>
               <l>At every ſtep, both he's, and ſhe's,</l>
               <l>To turn <hi>Aeneas</hi> back, and make him</l>
               <l>Follow the work he'd undertaken;</l>
               <l>Or if he would not turn, t' afford</l>
               <l>The Grace to turn him over-board.</l>
               <l>Thus to her footing the poor Jade,</l>
               <l>Out of all meaſure curſt and pray'd.</l>
               <l>Againſt her Love had ſo offended,</l>
               <l>Till dance and charm together ended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:65925:61"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nox erat &amp; placidum carpeba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t feſſa ſoporem</l>
                        <l>Corp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ra per terras, ſilvaque &amp; ſaeva quierant</l>
                        <l>Aequora——</l>
                        <l>Cum tacet omnis ager, pecudes, pictaeque volucres,</l>
                        <l>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>que lacus late liquidos, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>que aſpera dumis</l>
                        <l>Rura tenent, ſomno poſitae ſub nocte ſilenti</l>
                        <l>Lenibant curas.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 'Twas now the time when candles are</l>
               <l>Repriv'd by the Extinguiſher;</l>
               <l>When every thing to ſleep down lies,</l>
               <l>Dogs in their Kennels, Hogs in Sties;</l>
               <l>And men and women reſt their heads</l>
               <l>And heels, on flocks, or feather-beds.</l>
               <l>Now men, and fiſhes, birds, and beaſt,</l>
               <l>And every thing was laid to reſt;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>At non infelix animi Phoeniſſa: nec unquam</l>
                        <l>Solvitur in ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>s, oculiſque aut pectore noctem</l>
                        <l>Accipit:——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> All but the woful Queen (alaſs!)</l>
               <l>Who now was brought unto that paſs,</l>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:65925:61"/>
               <l>What with her love, and what with ſpight,</l>
               <l>She could not ſleep one wink all night.</l>
               <l>Her ſtomach now was piping hot,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">—Magnoque irarum fluctuat aeſtu.</note> It boyl'd and bubbled like a pot,</l>
               <l>And did ſo ſtrong a wambling keep,</l>
               <l>She fitter was to ſpew then ſleep.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Have you not ſeen an Animal</l>
               <l>Yclep't an horſe when in his ſtall,</l>
               <l>The Botts, that terrible diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Doth on his tender bowels ſeize,</l>
               <l>What groans he fetches, and what pranks</l>
               <l>He rowling playes upon the planks:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Dido</hi> croſt in her amours,</l>
               <l>Tumbled away her ſleeping hours.</l>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:65925:62"/>
               <l>Now on her back, and in ſuch faſhion,</l>
               <l>As if ſhe lay for conſolation,</l>
               <l>Now on her belly, now her ſide,</l>
               <l>All poſtures, and all wayes ſhe tri'd;</l>
               <l>But all in vain, nothing would do,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Ingeminant curae, rurſuſque reſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gens</l>
                        <l>Saevit amor.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Her heart was ſo oppreſt with wo,</l>
               <l>And love within her did ſo rumble,</l>
               <l>Shee could do nought but toſs, and tumble.</l>
               <l>At laſt in midſt of agitation,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sic ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſiſtit, ſecumque it a corde volutat,</l>
                        <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> quid agam?——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> She thus brake out into a paſſion;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which way poor <hi>Dido</hi> ſhould thou turn thee</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt cruel love, do's thus heart burn thee,</l>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:65925:62"/>
               <l>Thou haſt of hope not one poor ſpark left,</l>
               <l>Th' aſt brought thy hogs to a fair Market.</l>
               <l>Not one poor Dram of conſolation,</l>
               <l>O woman vile in deſperation!</l>
               <l>What ſhall I do in this condition,</l>
               <l>To keep me from the Worlds deriſion?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Rurſuſne procos i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>riſa priores</l>
                        <l>Experiar? Nomadumque petam con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ibia ſuppl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>x,</l>
                        <l>Quos ego ſum toties jam de dignita maritos?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Shall I invite to be my ſpouſe,</l>
               <l>Some one I have forbid my houſe?</l>
               <l>Some ſaucie, proud <hi>New-Indian</hi> Jack,</l>
               <l>And humbly beg of him to take</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Iliacas igitur claſſes atqae ultima Teucrum</l>
                        <l>fuſſ a ſequar?———</l>
                        <l>——Sola fuga nautas comitabor ovantes;</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> leavings, or like Trull here,</l>
               <l>Run away baſely with this Sculler.</l>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:65925:63"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>An Tyriis omnique manu ſtip ata meorum</l>
                        <l>Inſequar?——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Or ſhall I raiſe the Town in ſwarms,</l>
               <l>And bring him back by force of arms!</l>
               <l>Alaſs! I feat it is no boot!</l>
               <l>Fowl means will never bring him to't.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Quin morere, ut merita es: ſerroque averte dolorem.</note> No, No, I'le die! this halter yet,</l>
               <l>When all trades fail, ſhall do the feat.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Tu prima ſurentem</l>
                        <l>His germana m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lis oneras,——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Ah, Siſter, ſiſter! had'ſt not thou,</l>
               <l>Play'd Miſtreſs <hi>Quicklies</hi> office ſo,</l>
               <l>And ſooth'd me up till I grew jolly,</l>
               <l>I never had committed folly:</l>
               <l>No, had I made the leaſt reſiſtance,</l>
               <l>And kept the ſaucie Knave at diſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:65925:63"/>
               <l>I might have us'd him as my liſt,</l>
               <l>And ne'r been brought to had I wiſt,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Tantos illa ſuo rum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at pectore quaeſtus.</note> Thus lay the wretched Queen debating,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nan,</hi> Fortune, and her Lover rating.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Aeneas celſa in puppi——</l>
                        <l>carpebat ſomnos——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Whileſt he Drum-ful with his Potation,</l>
               <l>Ne'r dreaming on the doleful paſſion,</l>
               <l>He had moſt vilely left his drab in,</l>
               <l>Lay drunk and ſnoring in his Cabbin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Huic ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſorma Dei——</l>
                        <l>Obtulit in ſomnis————</l>
                        <l>Omnia Mercurio ſimilis——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But <hi>Merc'ry</hi> though he ſlept profoundly,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——rur ſuſque ita viſa monere eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                        <l>Nate Dea——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Made bold to beat up's Quarters roundly,</l>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:65925:64"/>
               <l>And thus 'gan rattle him: Thou louſie,</l>
               <l>Mangie, careleſs, drunken, drowſie</l>
               <l>Coxcomb; how oft muſt I be ſent</l>
               <l>Hither from Jove to complement</l>
               <l>Your worſhip to a reverent care,</l>
               <l>Of the young Baſtard here, your their?</l>
               <l>Whileſt faſt thouly'ſt tipled, or tipling;</l>
               <l>Nor car'ſt what danger the poor ſtripling</l>
               <l>Lies open to.<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——potes hoc ſub caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ducere ſomnos?</l>
                        <l>Nec que circumſtent te deind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> pericula cernis</l>
                        <l>Demens?——</l>
                        <l>Illa dolos—in pectore verſat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Y'ad beſt ſnore on,</l>
               <l>Some body will be here anon:</l>
               <l>Take to 'ther nap! Do! till the Queen come,</l>
               <l>She'l reckon with you for your in-come.</l>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:65925:64"/>
               <l>She'l rowſe ye faith! And (Goodman Letcher)</l>
               <l>Tis ten to one, with a good ſtretcher</l>
               <l>About you ears: Therefore my loving</l>
               <l>Acquaintance, you were beſt be<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non fugis hinc preceps dum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aecipitare poteſtas</l>
                        <l>Eia age, rumpe mords.———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> moving.</l>
               <l>Upon my word th' advice is wholſom,</l>
               <l>Stay not untill that angry ſoul come:</l>
               <l>For if thou doſt, mark what I ſay,</l>
               <l>And be'ſt not gone before't be day,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Jam mare turbari trabibus, ſaevaſque videbis</l>
                        <l>collucere facecs, &amp;c———</l>
                        <l>site his at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>igerit terris auroram ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>em.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> If <hi>Carthage</hi> been't about your ears</l>
               <l>As ſoon as ever day appears,</l>
               <l>And do not thraſh you back and ſide,</l>
               <l>Far worſe then <hi>Agamemnon</hi> did,</l>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:65925:65"/>
               <l>Thoſe of your woman-ſtealing rabble.</l>
               <l>Give me but ſix pence, if thou'rt able,</l>
               <l>And here's my hand, I do not ſport,</l>
               <l>I'le give thee twenty ſhillings for't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">—Sic fatus nocti ſe immiſcuit atrae.</note> Thus having ſaid, away he flies,</l>
               <l>Ere Toſs-pot could unglew his eyes,</l>
               <l>Which were ſo cemented in that caſe,</l>
               <l>The Page was got as far as <hi>Atlas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Back on his way e're he could free'um,</l>
               <l>From gowl and matter, fit to ſee him:</l>
               <l>But having ſtreakt, and yawn'd a while,</l>
               <l>Snorted, and kept the uſual coil</l>
               <l>That Drunkards uſe in ſuch like caſes,</l>
               <l>And made ſome dozen Devils faces:</l>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:65925:65"/>
               <l>At laſt he got his eyes unglew'd</l>
               <l>Into a pretty magnitude.</l>
               <l>He ſtar'd about to ſpie the Viſion</l>
               <l>Had giv'n that courteous admonition:</l>
               <l>But 'twas ſo dark, as well it might,</l>
               <l>Being 'twixt twelve and one at night;</l>
               <l>That had the nimble Currier</l>
               <l>In kindneſs ſtaid his leiſure there,</l>
               <l>Though clad in <hi>Fallſtaffs Kendal Green,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He coulc not poſſibly be ſeen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tum vero Aeneas ſubitis exterritus umbris</l>
                        <l>corripit è ſomno corpus, ſocioſque fatigat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> troubled herewithal,</l>
               <l>Seeing he could not ſee at all,</l>
               <l>Starts from the tilt where he had layn,</l>
               <l>And calls upon his mates amain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:65925:66"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Praecipites vigilate viri,—</note> Riſe Sirs (quoth he) and look about ye,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Deus aethere miſſus ab alto,</l>
                        <l>Feſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nare f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gam, tortoſque incidire funes</l>
                        <l>Ecce iter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m ſtimulat:—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> I've had from <hi>Jove</hi> another how-dee,</l>
               <l>His man was here, and calls to go ſtill,</l>
               <l>His ſweaty pumps are in my noſe ſtill.</l>
               <l>He ſwears and offer'd to lay odds on't,</l>
               <l>And if he ſay't, Ile lay my—on't.</l>
               <l>That if we do not leave the Dock,</l>
               <l>And get us hence by four a Clock,</l>
               <l>We ſhall be murther'd if we were</l>
               <l>Ten times as many as we are.</l>
               <l>Therefore I think it not amiſs for's</l>
               <l>To lanch, for there are rods in piſs for's.</l>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:65925:66"/>
               <l>Let us but ply our Oars like tall men,</l>
               <l>Till we be got clear out of all ken,</l>
               <l>Then if they have a mind to lace us,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Carthage</hi> if they can come trace us.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Sequimur te ſancte, deorum</l>
                        <l>Quiſquis es.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And thou (O <hi>Jove,</hi> top of my kin!)</l>
               <l>Who hitherto ſo kind haſt been,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Adſis, ô placiduſque juves &amp; ſydera coelo</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>extra ſeras!———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> If now thou ſtick, and do not fail's,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Dido</hi> whiſtle in our tails.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus having ſpoken, and thus pray'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Dixit, vaginaque eripit enſem</l>
                        <l>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lmineum, ſtrictoque ferit retinacula ferro.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Forthwith he drew his doughty blade,</l>
               <l>And at one ſlaſh to all mens wonder,</l>
               <l>Cut the Boats triple cord aſunder.</l>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:65925:67"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Idem omnes ſimul ardor habet——</l>
                        <l>———rapiuntque ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ntque,</l>
                        <l>Littora deſeruere————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> At which the Gang, ſpur'd by ſo ample,</l>
               <l>So mighty and renown'd example,</l>
               <l>Cut all the reſt; nor ſtaying brooks,</l>
               <l>But let the Devil take the hooks,</l>
               <l>And ſhipping Oars to work they fall,</l>
               <l>Like men that row'd for good and all.</l>
               <l>Had it been day, no doubt one might</l>
               <l>Have then beheld a gallant ſight.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi>'s great whiskers had not been</l>
               <l>So neatly <note n="z" place="margin">———&amp; coerula verrunt.</note> bruſht as they were then</l>
               <l>Of many a year: Crabs that did neſt</l>
               <l>Full deep therein, could take no reſt:</l>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:65925:67"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Adnixi torquent ſpumas.——</note> They lather'd him in the great Baſon</l>
               <l>So admirably well that <hi>Jaſon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Although he ſhav'd the golden fleece,</l>
               <l>Ne're waſht him half ſo well as theſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Et jam prima novo ſpargebat lumine terras</l>
                        <l>Tithoni croceum linquens <hi>Aurora</hi> cubile.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aurora</hi> now, who I muſt tell ye,</l>
               <l>Was gript with dolours in her belly,</l>
               <l>Starts from her couch, and o're her head</l>
               <l>Slipping on petticoat of red,</l>
               <l>Forth of the morning doors ſhe goes,</l>
               <l>In haſty wiſe, to pluck a Roſe;</l>
               <l>When <hi>Dido,</hi> who was broad awake,</l>
               <l>Hearing the ruſty hinges creak,</l>
               <l>Ran to her <note n="c" place="margin">Regina è ſpeculis ut primum albe ſcere lucem.</note> peeping hole to ſpy,</l>
               <l>What was become o'th' <hi>Trojanry.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:65925:68"/>
               <l>But out alaſs! <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Vidit &amp; aequatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>laſſem procedere velis,</l>
                        <l>Littoraque &amp; va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uos ſenſit ſine remige portus.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> The Devil a ſail</l>
               <l>Was left i'th' port; bare as my nail</l>
               <l>The Dock was ſtript; whilſt far from ſhore</l>
               <l>They row'd, as they ne'r row'd before.</l>
               <l>At which ſad ſight, in wrath (God bleſs us!)</l>
               <l>(o) Tearing her dainty yellow treſſes,</l>
               <l>She ſighing ſaid, Was ever ſeen</l>
               <l>So pitiful an undone Queen!</l>
               <l>And ſhall this filthy <hi>Trojan</hi> Royſter</l>
               <l>Undo, as one would do an Oyſter,</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Dido</hi> thus, and run away,</l>
               <l>Maugre what I can do or ſay!<note place="margin">(e)
<lg>
                        <l>Flaventeſque abſciſſa comas; Proh! <hi>Jupiter!</hi> ibit</l>
                        <l>Hic ait, &amp; noſtris illuſerit advena regnis?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:65925:68"/>
               <l>Hey, how the treach'rous wenching knave</l>
               <l>Bounces, and vaults from wave to wave,</l>
               <l>As he were making Ducks and Drakes,</l>
               <l>With Wherries upon Neptunes lakes!</l>
               <l>The Devil ſure farts in his poop,</l>
               <l>And puffs his kicking Sculler up;</l>
               <l>Or elſe ſome durty Suburb drab</l>
               <l>Has helpt the Raſcal to a clap,</l>
               <l>And ſent a running-Nag to Sea,</l>
               <l>He could not elſe make ſo much way.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non arma expedient? tot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>que ex urbe ſequemur?</l>
                        <l>————ite;</l>
                        <l>Ferte citi flammas, date vela, impellite remos.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Cannot I burn, nor ſink their floats,</l>
               <l>A louſie fleet of rotten boats!</l>
               <l>Yes I'me a Queen, to ſee my people;</l>
               <l>Let none remember he's a Cripple:</l>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:65925:69"/>
               <l>But run, and row, ſound, and unſound,</l>
               <l>And thoſe you kill not, bring home bound!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quid loquor? aut ubi ſum? quae mentem inſania mutat?</l>
                        <l>Infelix <hi>Dido?</hi>———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But tarry goody Magiſtrate,</l>
               <l>Your big commands come now too late.</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Dido,</hi> ſorrow makes thee giddy,</l>
               <l>They'r got to Sea five Leagues already.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Nunc te facta impia tangunt;</l>
                        <l>Tum decuit, cum ſceptra dabas.——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Queen thou art mortal, and muſt die</l>
               <l>A ſacrifice to Letchery.</l>
               <l>Time was thou migh'ſt have ſomething done,</l>
               <l>But now farewel Dominion.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——En dextra fideſque;</l>
                        <l>Quem ſecum patrios ajunt portare Penates,</l>
                        <l>Quem ſubiiſſe humer is conſectum aetate parentem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> This was your huffing <hi>Trojan</hi> Captain,</l>
               <l>That his fair Mothers ſmock was lapt in.</l>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:65925:69"/>
               <l>Of twenty <hi>Greeks,</hi> this was the <hi>Cob,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And brought his Gods away in's Phob,</l>
               <l>And through the fire a pick a pack,</l>
               <l>Bore the old ſinner on his back,</l>
               <l>Bed-rid <hi>Anchiſes;</hi> this was he</l>
               <l>Made the brave voyage o're the ſea.</l>
               <l>This was your truſty <hi>Trojan,</hi> this:</l>
               <l>Now he ſhows what a man he is!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non potui abreptum divellere corpus, &amp; undis</l>
                        <l>Spargere?———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Whilſt he was here, why did I not</l>
               <l>Cut the falſe Rogues devouring throat;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Non ipſum abſumere ferro</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aſcanium,</hi>——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Or of his baſtard make a Pye,</l>
               <l>And being bak'd in paſte of Rye,</l>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:65925:70"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">—<hi>Patriiſque epuland um apponere menſis?</hi>
                  </note> Make the good trencher-man his naſty</l>
               <l>Sire, eat his brat for Mutton-paſty!</l>
               <l>Why did I not, ere this diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Kill him, and all his treacherous</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Natumque patremqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Com genere extinxem; memet ſuper ipſa dediſſem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> race?</l>
               <l>I then had dy'd reveng'd, where I</l>
               <l>Shall now depart moſt ſneakingly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Sol, qui terrarum flammis opera om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia luſtras;</note> Thou <hi>Sol,</hi> who did'ſt in pimping ſort,</l>
               <l>Becauſe thou would'ſt not ſpoil our ſport,</l>
               <l>Creep into clouds, that rainy weather:</l>
               <l>And you that brought young folks together,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tuque harum interpres curarum, &amp; conſcia <hi>Juno,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nocturniſque Hecate———</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t dirae ult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Procureſs <hi>Juno, Jove</hi> and all</l>
               <l>Ye members of <hi>Olympus</hi> hall,</l>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:65925:70"/>
               <l>I charge ye, as y' are folks of faſhion,</l>
               <l>Grant this my lateſt<note n="q" place="margin">——<hi>Noſtras audite preces</hi>——</note> ſupplication.</l>
               <l>If nothing can this Rogue withſtand,</l>
               <l>But that he muſt get ſafe to <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———Si tangere portus</l>
                        <l>Infandum caput, ac terris ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>re neceſſe eſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> land,</l>
               <l>Let it be ſuch a land as he</l>
               <l>Had better farr upon the ſea,</l>
               <l>With all his com-rogues have been drown'd,</l>
               <l>Than ſuch a wretched place have found.</l>
               <l>May he, where he expects his Leaſes,</l>
               <l>Nere know what ſuch a thing as Peace is;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Bello audacis populi vexatus, &amp; armis,</l>
                        <l>Finibus extorris———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> But be drub'd dayly back and ſide</l>
               <l>Till his bones rattle in his hide.</l>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:65925:71"/>
               <l>May he ne're ſleep an hour in quiet,</l>
               <l>But be diſturb'd with rout and riot;</l>
               <l>Black be his dayes, and may his nights</l>
               <l>Swarm with Hob-Goblins, Ghoſts, and Sprites:</l>
               <l>May ſtrangers daunt him with Bravado's</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">——Complexu avulſus <hi>lüli,</hi>
                  </note> And Spirits ſon to the <hi>Barbado</hi>'s:</l>
               <l>May he at laſt fall worſe then Sea-ſick,</l>
               <l>And find no Quack to give him Phyſick:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Auxilium imploret———</note> No help for money, or for love found;</l>
               <l>But let him lie, and rot above ground.</l>
               <l>May none give houſe-room to the Mungril;</l>
               <l>But let him periſh on ſome<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Videa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>que ſuorum</l>
                        <l>Funera———</l>
                        <l>—Mediaeque inhumatus arena.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Dung-hill.</l>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:65925:71"/>
               <l>And when his treach'rous ſoul's departed,</l>
               <l>Let his foul Carcaſs be deſerted,</l>
               <l>As Traitors quarters, men expoſe.</l>
               <l>To Hogs, and Dogs, and Kites, and Crows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Haec precor; hanc vocem extremam—fundo.</note> This my laſt pray'r is, hear it then,</l>
               <l>I ſhall ne're trouble you agen.</l>
               <l>And be't your care ye <hi>Tyrian</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tum vos ô <hi>Tyrii,</hi> ſtirpem &amp; genus omne fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Exercete odi is, cinerique haec mittite noſtro</l>
                        <l>Munera———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Nation,</l>
               <l>To plague this wicked generation.</l>
               <l>Kill 'um like rats, that I may have</l>
               <l>Heapes of the Rogues pil'd o're my grave:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Pugnent ipſique nepotes;</l>
                        <l>Exoriare aliquis noſtris ex oſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us idtor.</l>
                        <l>—Nullus amor populis, nec faedera ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And may thoſe children that are yet</l>
               <l>To bear, and thoſe that are to get,</l>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:65925:72"/>
               <l>Torment them ſtill by land and water,</l>
               <l>And ſtill may thoſe that follow after,</l>
               <l>Hate worſe and worſe, that ſo it fall,</l>
               <l>The laſt may hate them worſt of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Haec ait————</note> This ſaid, ſhe let a groan, and ſigh'd</l>
               <l>A doleful ſigh, that prophecy'd</l>
               <l>Her thred was ſpun, and that the <hi>Parcae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Would ſhortly cut it without mercy.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Et Partes animum verſahat in omnes,</l>
                        <l>Inviſam quaerens quamprimum abrumpere lucem.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> In mind ſhe weigh'd, as ſhe fat crying,</l>
               <l>What kind of Death was beſt to die in.</l>
               <l>Poyſon ſhe thought would not be quick,</l>
               <l>And which was worſe, would make her ſick.</l>
               <l>That being therefore wav'd, ſhe thought,</l>
               <l>That neatly cutting her own throat,</l>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:65925:72"/>
               <l>Might ſerve to do her buſineſs for her,</l>
               <l>But that ſhe thought upon with horror,</l>
               <l>Becauſe 'twould hurt her; neither could,</l>
               <l>She well endure to fee her bloud.</l>
               <l>The next came in her thoughts was drowning,</l>
               <l>That way ſhe thought 'twould be a done thing,</l>
               <l>Soon, and with ſome delight; for why</l>
               <l>Sorrow had made her Grace adry.</l>
               <l>But then again ſhe fell a thinking,</l>
               <l>She ſhould be ſomething long a ſinking,</l>
               <l>Having been ever light of members,</l>
               <l>And to diſſwade her more, remembers,</l>
               <l>'Twould ſpoil the cloaths might do ſome one</l>
               <l>Credit, when ſhe was dead and gone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On theſe mature deliberations,</l>
               <l>Shee lik'd none of theſe dying faſhions:</l>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:65925:73"/>
               <l>But looking up, and ſeeing the Rope</l>
               <l>Ty'd to the beam i'th' Chamber top,</l>
               <l>With neat alluring Nooſe, her ſick-Grace</l>
               <l>E'en long'd to wear it for a Neck-lace:</l>
               <l>And in that circle in concluſion,</l>
               <l>She prick'd the point of reſolution.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Tum breviter <hi>Bareen</hi> nutricem affata Sichaei.</note> But an old woman being by her,</l>
               <l>One of her chattels brought from <hi>Tyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>An ancient heir-loom to the Queen,</l>
               <l>'Cauſe ſhe her husbands nurſe had been:</l>
               <l>She meant to ſend her firſt away,</l>
               <l>On ſleeveleſs errand (as we ſay,)</l>
               <l>That ſhe might have her ſwing alone,</l>
               <l>To do her execution.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:65925:73"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Annam</hi> cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a mihi autrix huc ſiſte ſororem:</l>
                        <l>Dic corpus properet fluviali ſparge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e lymp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a,</l>
                        <l>——Tuque ipſa pia t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ge tempora vitta.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cicely</hi> (quoth ſhe) go to my Siſter,</l>
               <l>Bid her tie up her head, and wiſh her</l>
               <l>To waſh her hands in Bran, or Flower,</l>
               <l>And do you in like manner ſcoure</l>
               <l>Your dirty Golls; for I intend to</l>
               <l>Make a good Cheeſe, and for a friend too,</l>
               <l>O'th' mornings milk; let it be her care</l>
               <l>To take the great Braſs-pan i'th' Larder,</l>
               <l>And ſile the milk into't: and hear ye,</l>
               <l>Take you the large Cheeſe-fat i'th' Dayry,</l>
               <l>And ſcoure it clean with ſand; bid <hi>Jone</hi> too</l>
               <l>Get on the pot, that ſhe may come too,</l>
               <l>And when the Cheeſe is come, but brake it,</l>
               <l>And call: for I'le come help to make it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:65925:74"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">—Illa gradum ſtudio celerabat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nili.</note> The hobling Trot limps down the ſtairs,</l>
               <l>And now the deſp'rate Queen prepares;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Et tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pida—&amp; pallida morte ſutura.</note> Although her woful heart did pantle,</l>
               <l>To make her ſelf a ſad example.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Interiora domus irrumpit limina, &amp; altos</l>
                        <l>Conſcendit furibunda rogos———</l>
                        <l>——Paulum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ymis &amp; mente morata.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Towards the fatal ſtring ſhe moves</l>
               <l>With tardy pace, as it behoves</l>
               <l>Thoſe who by <hi>Nicholas</hi> led aſtray,</l>
               <l>Wilfully make themſelves away.</l>
               <l>When ſhe came underneath the halter,</l>
               <l>The colour in her face did alter;</l>
               <l>Whilſt down her cheeks round liquor rowls,</l>
               <l>As if her eyes had been at Bowls.</l>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:65925:74"/>
               <l>Firſt ſhe beholds with trickling eies,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hic poſtquam <hi>Iliacas</hi> veſtes, notumque cubile</l>
                        <l>Conſpexit,—————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> his moſt dear diſguiſe:</l>
               <l>And as the Trowſes ſhe ſurvey'd,</l>
               <l>Reflecting how ſhe' ad been betray'd:</l>
               <l>Sighing cry'd out,<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lces exuviae, dum fata, Deuſque ſinebant.</l>
                        <l>———Dixitque no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſſima verba.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Oh! thou who wert,</l>
               <l>The joy and comfort of my heart,</l>
               <l>Whilſt casket to my deareſt Jewel;</l>
               <l>But ſince the Fates have been ſo cruel,</l>
               <l>My grief, and ſhame, farewell for ever;</l>
               <l>And here I propheſie, that never,</l>
               <l>VVhoever may hereafter wear thee,</l>
               <l>Shall mortal <hi>Bilbo</hi> ere come near thee.</l>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:65925:75"/>
               <l>Farewel, my lateſt leave I take,</l>
               <l>And kiſs the Caſe for Ho-boys ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus having ſaid, ſhe mounts the table,</l>
               <l>Becauſe though tall, ſhe was not able</l>
               <l>To reach the halter, that muſt tie</l>
               <l>Her faſt to doleful deſtinie:</l>
               <l>And having like too apt a Scholler,</l>
               <l>Thruſt her plumpe neck into the coller,</l>
               <l>As'tis, you know, the hanging faſhion,</l>
               <l>She thus began her laſt Oration:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">VIXI, &amp; quem dederat curſum fortuna, peregi.</note> That I have liv'd (quoth ſhe) and how,</l>
               <l>I doubt (alaſs!) too many know;</l>
               <l>But that I now will die, is known</l>
               <l>To no one but my ſelf alone,</l>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:65925:75"/>
               <l>And if I Natures debt do pay,</l>
               <l>And hang my ſelf before my days,</l>
               <l>The cenſuring world can ſay but this,</l>
               <l>That I'me the better pay miſtriſs:</l>
               <l>And though I die a death, they ſay,</l>
               <l>Makes ſufferers themſelves bewray</l>
               <l>And die uncleanly corps; yet I</l>
               <l>Shall leave, although I purging die,</l>
               <l>And go out ſtrong as Candle-ſnuff,</l>
               <l>A fame ſhall favour ſweet enough.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Urbem praeclaram ſtatui, mea moenia vidi;</l>
                        <l>Ulta virum Paenas iaim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>co à ſrat. e recepi.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> For murther'd ſpouſe I've made amends yet</l>
               <l>As far as ſtealing could revenge it,</l>
               <l>And make <hi>Pygmalion</hi> that undid us,</l>
               <l>Pay ſauce for making people widows.</l>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:65925:76"/>
               <l>And at my proper coſt and charges</l>
               <l>A village built, which for its largneſs,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Felix, heu nimium ſelix, ſi littora tantum</l>
                        <l>Nunquam <hi>Darnaniae</hi> tetigiſſent noſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> carinae!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> In a few years, might well have grown</l>
               <l>To be a pretty Market-town,</l>
               <l>Had not this <hi>Trojan</hi> varlet come</l>
               <l>T'undo what all my care had done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then (going to turn off)<note n="o" place="margin">Sed moriamur ait; ſic, ſic juvat ire ſub umbras.</note> But muſt</l>
               <l>I go (quoth ſhe) and is it juſt,</l>
               <l>I die like Felon vile or Traytor?</l>
               <l>Sans vengeance on this Fornicator.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hauriat bune oculis ignem crudelis ab alto</l>
                        <l>Dardanus, &amp; noſtrae ſecum ferat omnia mortis.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> And whilſt the Stallion proudly ſtalks it,</l>
               <l>Muſt I be thus han'g'd up for Hawks-meat?</l>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:65925:76"/>
               <l>Yes die, as 'twas foretold thee long ſince,</l>
               <l>If but to trouble the knaves conſcience:</l>
               <l>Then 'cauſe ſhe would to part the ſweeter,</l>
               <l>A portion of <hi>Hopkins</hi> meeter;</l>
               <l>As people uſe at execution,</l>
               <l>For the decorum of concluſion,</l>
               <l>Being too ſad to ſing, ſhe ſayes</l>
            </lg>
            <l>———</l>
            <lg>
               <l>Which with a grace like his that pen'd i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>To her great comfort, being ended,</l>
               <l>And ceremonies now compleat,</l>
               <l>Proceeding to the final feat.</l>
               <l>Thus, thus (quoth ſhe) to ſhades of night</l>
               <l>I go, and thus I take my flight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:65925:77"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Dixcrat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> atque illam media inter talia.—</note> With that ſhe from the table ſwong,</l>
               <l>And happy 'twas the rope was ſtrong</l>
               <l>Enough, in ſuch a ſwing to ſtop her,</l>
               <l>Her Grace might elſe have broke her crupper.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Non aliter quam ſi immiſſis ruat hoſtibus omnis</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Carthago.</hi>———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> So have I ſeen in Forreſt tall,</l>
               <l>From friendly cup the Acorn fall,</l>
               <l>And Bully tumble from the tree,</l>
               <l>As ripe for hanging; Down fell ſhe.</l>
               <l>She capr'd twice, or thrice, moſt finely;</l>
               <l>But th' Rope imbrac'd her neck ſo kindly:</l>
               <l>Till at the laſt, in mortal trance,</l>
               <l>She did conclude the diſmal dance.</l>
               <l>A yellow aromatick matter</l>
               <l>Dropt from her heels, commixt with water,</l>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:65925:77"/>
               <l>Which ſinking through the Chamber floor,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mor ad alta</l>
                        <l>Atria; concuſſam bacchatur fama per urbem</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Set all the houſe in ſad uproar.</l>
               <l>All at the firſt that they amiſs thought,</l>
               <l>Was that her Grace had miſt the piſs-pot:</l>
               <l>But when the ſtairs they had aſcended,</l>
               <l>And ſaw her Majeſty ſuſpended,</l>
               <l>The ſervants frighted paſt their ſenſes,</l>
               <l>Tumbled o're Buffets, Forms, and Benches,</l>
               <l>And ran to all the near abidings,</l>
               <l>With open cry to tell the tidings.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lamentis, gemituque, &amp; ſoemineo ululatu</l>
                        <l>Tecta fremunt, reſonat magnis plangoribus aether:</l>
                        <l>Non aliter quam ſi, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>——</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Even like unto the diſmal yowl,</l>
               <l>When triſtfull Dogs at midnight howl:</l>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:65925:78"/>
               <l>Or like the Dirges that through noſe</l>
               <l>Humme out to daunt their <hi>Pagan</hi> foes,</l>
               <l>When holy Round-heads go to battle,</l>
               <l>With ſuch a yell did <hi>Carthage</hi> rattle.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Audiit ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>imis, trepidoque exterrita curſu,</l>
                        <l>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ibus ora ſoror ſoedans, &amp; pectora pugnis,</l>
                        <l>Per medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uit.————</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> At the firſt news poor <hi>Nancy</hi> skreeks,</l>
               <l>And tearing hair, and ſcratching cheeks,</l>
               <l>Ran up the ſtairs, and like a fell-ſhrow,</l>
               <l>Made all that ſtopt her, feel her elbow:</l>
               <l>Till having joſtled all oppoſers,</l>
               <l>And thruſt ſome twenty on thier noſes;</l>
               <l>At laſt the place ſhe ſet her feet on,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Dido</hi> hung to dry, or ſweeten.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:65925:78"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Hoc illud germana ſuit?——</note> Was it for this ah! ſiſter, ſiſter!</l>
               <l>That I was ſent to Gaffer-<hi>Twiſter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To buy a Rope;<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>——Me fraude petcbas?</l>
                        <l>Hoc rogus iſte mihi, hoc ignes araeque parabant?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> was this (quoth ſhe)</l>
               <l>Your fine device to cozen me?</l>
               <l>Could none a halter elſe prepare ye,</l>
               <l>But I muſt be made acceſſary!</l>
               <l>Why knew I not thy dire intent, as</l>
               <l>I ſtill thy chiefeſt confident was!</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———Comitém<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e ſororem</l>
                        <l>Spreviſti moriens? eadem me ad ſata vocaſſes:</l>
                        <l>Idem ambas ferro doler, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> What didſt thou know, but kindly I</l>
               <l>Might e'en have hang'd for company:</l>
               <l>But in thy ruin, I and all</l>
               <l>Thy people ſuffer, great and ſmall.</l>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:65925:79"/>
               <l>And in this wilful woman-ſlaughter,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Extinxti te, meque, ſoror, populumque, patreſque</l>
                        <l>Sidonios, urbemque tuam; date vulnera lymphis,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Th'aſt hang'd up <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſon &amp; daughter.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Albuam———</note> But ſtay, methinks I am not haſty,</l>
               <l>To cloſe thoſe eyes that ſtare ſo gaſtly.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">——Sic fata, gradus evaſerat altos,</note> Which ſaid, her buttocks on the board</l>
               <l>She ſos'd, that all the Chamber roar'd.</l>
               <l>And being active Laſs and light,</l>
               <l>At one jump more ſtood bolt upright.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sem ani nemque ſinu german<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m amplexa fovebat</l>
                        <l>Cum gemitu, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>——</l>
                        <l>Ter ſeſe attollens———</l>
                        <l>Ter revoluta toro eſt—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Thrice in her arms did <hi>Nancy</hi> catch her,</l>
               <l>Thrice thump't her boſome to diſpatch her.</l>
               <l>And thrice her lateſt breath did roar,</l>
               <l>In hollow ſound, at poſtern door.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:65925:79"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Tum <hi>Juno</hi>——</note> Then <hi>Juno</hi> who had ever been</l>
               <l>As 'twere ſworn ſiſter to the Queen:</l>
               <l>Hearing the lamentable cryes,</l>
               <l>That from her Village pierc'd the skies;</l>
               <l>Down towards <hi>Carthage</hi> bent her looks,</l>
               <l>Where ſeeing all things off the hooks,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Dido</hi> in unſeemly ſort,</l>
               <l>Hang dangling there, being ſorry for't,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">——longum miſerata dolorem.</note> And loth a Queen in hempen tackle,</l>
               <l>Should to <hi>Plebeians</hi> be ſpectacle;</l>
               <l>She call'd a little Emiſſary,</l>
               <l>That us'd her Embaſſies to carry,</l>
               <l>One Miſtriſs <hi>Iris:</hi> A main pretty,</l>
               <l>Nimble houſe-wife, yes and a witty,</l>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:65925:80"/>
               <l>One that if bidden once, would do't,</l>
               <l>And had the length of <hi>Juno</hi>'s foot</l>
               <l>So right, that for her parts and feature,</l>
               <l>She was become her Miſtreſs creature.</l>
               <l>This girle was born (as Poets hint to's,)</l>
               <l>At a ſmall Hamblet neer <hi>Olympus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And though by birth a Dyers daughter,</l>
               <l>Yet had her friends full well up-brought her,</l>
               <l>And becauſe <hi>Juno</hi> gave great wages,</l>
               <l>Preferr'd her thither for a Pageſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her <hi>Juno</hi> call'd away from ſtarching,</l>
               <l>And big with tears, bid her be marching,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>———<hi>Irim</hi> demiſit <hi>Olympo,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Quae luct intem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>imam n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xoſque reſolveret artus.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Put on her wings, and ſwiftly clip it,</l>
               <l>To cut down <hi>Dido</hi> from the Gibbet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:65925:80"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iris</hi> when young, had learn'd to flie</l>
               <l>(As youth is full of waggery)</l>
               <l>Of a tame Jack-daw that ſhe had,</l>
               <l>And for her journeys, lately made</l>
               <l>Fine party-colour'd wings to flie in,</l>
               <l>No worſe then of her Fathers Dying;</l>
               <l>Who knowing that his daughter was</l>
               <l>To be preferr'd to ſuch a place,</l>
               <l>And what ſhe muſt b' imployed about,</l>
               <l>Had ſpared no coſt to ſet her out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>go <hi>Iris</hi> croc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>s per coelum roſcida pennis,</l>
                        <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lle trahens varios adverſo ſolo colo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es,</l>
                        <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>volat.———</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> At the command of Heaven's Goddeſs,</l>
               <l>She ties theſe wings faſt to her bodies,</l>
               <l>Which waving, did adorn the skie,</l>
               <l>With all the fair variety</l>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:65925:81"/>
               <l>Of colours, that the Rain-bow ſhows</l>
               <l>When clad in her moſt gawdy cloths.</l>
               <l>Full ſwift ſhe flew, till coming near</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſhe made a Cancelleer,</l>
               <l>And then a ſtoop, when having ſpy'd</l>
               <l>Queen <hi>Dido</hi>'s window ſtaring wide;</l>
               <l>(Set open you may well preſume,</l>
               <l>(As there was cauſe) to air the room,)</l>
               <l>She nimbly, to all folks amazement,</l>
               <l>Whips like a Swallow through the caſement.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Et ſupra caput aſtitit. Hunc ego Diti</l>
                        <l>Sacrum juſſa fero; teque iſlo corpere ſolvo.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> O're <hi>Dido</hi>'s head, ſhe took her ſtand,</l>
               <l>And cry'd, whilſt flouriſhing a brand,</l>
               <l>Sent down from <hi>Juno</hi> Queen come I</l>
               <l>Epilogue to this Tragedie.</l>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:65925:81"/>
               <l>And thus O <hi>Dido</hi> let thee looſe,</l>
               <l>From twitch of ſuffocating nooſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Sic ait——</note> Which ſaid, and toſſing high her blade</l>
               <l>With great dexterity, the Maid</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>—Et dextra crinem ſee at: omnis &amp; una</l>
                        <l>Dilapſus calor, atque in ventos vita receſſit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> Oh wonderfull! even at one ſide-blow</l>
               <l>Spoyl'd a good Rope, and down dropt <hi>Dido.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:65925:82"/>
            <head>A Liſt of ſome Choice Poems printed for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the Gun in <hi>lvy-lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>SCarronnides,</hi> or <hi>Virgile Traveſtie,</hi> a Mock-Poem: being the Firſt Book of <hi>Virgils Aeneis</hi> in <hi>Engliſh, Burleſque:</hi> by the ſame Author.</item>
               <item>Poems
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lyrique,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Hen. Bold.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Macronique,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Hen. Bold.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Heroique,</hi> &amp;c. by Mr. <hi>Hen. Bold.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Songs and Poems by Mr. <hi>A. Brome,</hi> the ſecond Edition.</item>
               <item>All the Songs and Poems on the Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from 1640, till 1661. by Perſons of Quality.</item>
               <item>Songs and Poems by the VVits of both Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Playes.</head>
               <item>The Engliſh More.</item>
               <item>The Love ſick Court.</item>
               <item>The New Academy.</item>
               <item>The VVeeding of <hi>Covent Garden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Royal Exchange.</item>
               <item>The Jovial Crew, <hi>or</hi> The Merry Beggars.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All by Mr. <hi>Richard Brome.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65925:82"/>
                  <p>H B</p>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Henry Brome</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
